commence if we may. I declare open uh this hearing of the house of representatives standing committee on economics for the review of the reserve bank of Australia annual report 2025.
want to begin by acknowledging the Nanal and Nambbury peoples who are the traditional custodians of the lands on which we meet today paying respects to elders past and present and I also
extend that respect to the Aboriginal and toouristr islander peoples joining us today. I welcome representatives of the Reserve Bank of Australia as well as members of the public and media in the
room and those watching online. The hearing comes at a consequential time for the Australian and world economies. Our economy has continued to grow in difficult global circumstances. The
latest national accounts show real GDP increased by4% in the June quarter and 2.1% over the year with growth increasingly supported by private demand. While unemployment
remains low by historical standards at 4.5%, real wages grew by 0.2% in the quarter but fell 0.8% in the un in unrounded through the year terms. Even with those figures, annual real
wages have grown for eight of the last 11 quarters. Notably, the challenges confronting Australia are the same challenges confronting economies world over, including productivity growth, the
impact of rising global bond yields, and the effect of geopolitical instability. The RBA's increased the cash rate by 75 basis points during 2026, taking it to 4.35%
and held the rate unchanged in August. The conflict in the Middle East has imposed a serious human toll and remains a major inflationary pressure. Disruptions to energy production and
shipping have generated substantial volatility in oil, gas, other commodity prices with higher costs flowing into transport production, consumer prices. Yesterday, the US Federal Reserve raised
interest rates for the first time since 2023. The European Central Bank raised rates last week. The treasur has pointed out this week that the market is now pricing in an interest rate hike in
every single major advanced economy. Australia's gross debt as a share of our economy is much less than half of the US, less than half of Canada and the UK, less than a quarter of the gross debt to
GDP and Japan. Meanwhile, artificial intelligence presents Australia with pathways to lift productivity, business investment, and living standards. However, concerns
remain around higherend risks of AI and potential employment impacts. Additionally, questions remain in some quarters about the prospect of a rupture of the AI bubble and its economic
repercussions. The speed and scale of the investment boom in data center construction in Australia has been considerable. And having said that, questions have also been raised about
the pressure this might place on energy and water supply along with the effect of competition for skilled labor in the construction sector. Against that backdrop, today's hearing
is an opportunity to better understand how the RBA is balancing these global and domestic forces, how it sees the outlook for inflation, growth, productivity, and interest rates in the
period ahead. In accordance with the committee's resolution of 31 July 2025, this hearing will be broadcast on the parliament's website. The proof and official transcripts of the proceedings
will be published on that website. And I remember a remind I should say or present as that as chair I'll ensure that proceedings are conducted in an orderly respectful courteous way. Those
present are advised that filming and recording by the media is permitted during the hearing. However, we ask that members of the media present or listening report the committee's
proceedings fairly and accurately. media present are also asked to conduct themselves in a way that doesn't interfere with proceedings and must not encroach on the committee's work area or
film or photograph documents or devices of committee members, witnesses or others. I now welcome representatives of the Reserve Bank of Australia to give evidence and for the Hansard record,
could you please state your full names and the capacity in which you appear before the committee? Governor U Michelle Bulock, Governor, Reserve Bank of Australia. Andrew Houseer, deputy governor.
Bradley Jones, assistant governor, financial system. Sarah Hunter, assistant governor, economic. Thank you very much. I remind you uh that although the committee does not
require you to give evidence under oath, this hearing is a legal proceeding of the parliament and therefore has the same standing as proceedings of the house. The giving of false or misleading
evidence is a serious matter may be regarded as contempt of parliament. The evidence given today will be recorded by Hansard and attracts parliamentary privilege. With all that, Governor, I
now invite you to make an opening statement before we proceed to questions. Thank you. Thank you very much, chair, and good morning uh to other members of the committee as well. Um so my colleagues
and I are very pleased to be here today to answer your questions. I think these hearings are an important part of the accountability process for the Reserve Bank. So, as you know, our purpose is to
promote the economic prosperity and welfare of the Australian people now and into the future. One way we do this is by setting monetary policy to achieve low and stable inflation and full
employment and by supporting the stability of the financial system. But we also promote the prosperity and welfare of Australians across the full range of our responsibilities which
include supporting a reliable, efficient and competitive payment system, delivering efficient and effective banking services to Australian government agencies and providing secure
and reliable banknotes in Australia to Australians. Since the committee's previous public hearing with the RBA in February, the monetary policy board has tightened has t tightened monetary policy by
increasing the cash rate target by 50 basis points with the goal of returning inflation to target. This has taken the cumulative increase this year to 75 basis points. So, I'm going to start
with some background uh to these decisions and the outlook for the Australian economy. Then I'll provide an update on the payment system and cash distribution. And I'll finish off with
some remarks on how we're strengthening the RBA to position it to meet the challenges of the future. So as you know, the monetary policy board sets monetary policy such that
inflation is expected to return to the midpoint of the 2 to 3% target range. There's flexibility around the time frame over which we meet our inflation objective to balance this with meeting
our full employment objective. So turning to the first part of our mandate, inflation fell significantly from its peak of 7.9% at the end of 2022 to be within the 2 to 3% target range
for a period in 2024 and 2025. But inflation picked up over the second half of 2025 and has remained above target since then. Over the past year, both headline and underlying measures of
inflation were around or a little above three and a half%. The increase in inflation partly reflects reflects capacity pressures in the Australian economy and the conflict
in the Middle East has added to these inflation pressures. Higher oil prices have increased inflation directly through their impact on petrol prices. But it's also had an indirect impact as
many firms have passed input cost pressures arising from elevated fuel prices through to the prices of other goods and services. Because of these capacity pressures and the Middle East
conflict, inflation is likely to remain elevated for some time. I'll turn to our policy response shortly. But first, I wanted to update you on the second part of our mandate. Various indicator
various indicators continue to suggest that labor market conditions remain close to but a little tighter than full employment. The unemployment rate at 4.5% is low by historical standards and
the share of population with a job is close to a record high. This is a welcome outcome for those individuals, their families and the wider Australian economy. So, as I mentioned earlier, the monetary
policy board has increased the cash rate by 75 basis points this year to help reduce inflation. Inflation is too high. We're focused on getting it back down and making sure that it does not become
embedded into price and wage setting decisions. Our latest forecasts, which were published with the August statement on monetary policy, suggested that inflation will not return to around the
midpoint of the target range until late 2027. At the time of the August board meeting, we assess that the risks to that outlook were skewed to the upside. Developments since then suggest that
although growth in the Australian economy is slowing, some of these upside risks to inflation appear to be materializing. Global cost pressures have increased. The Middle East conflict, the AI boom,
and extreme weather events are contributing to upward pressure on a range of energy, agricultural, and technology related prices. There is little sign of resolution in the Middle
East conflict. Oil and related prices have increased sharply again and will add directly to inflation. Through our liaison program, we're hearing that many firms are passing on higher input costs.
This was expected. But it is important that these effects remain contained and do not become embedded into wage and price setting decisions. Otherwise, inflation could
prove more persistent and require a stronger policy response. We're not alone in being concerned about this. Central banks in many other advanced economies are responding to this global
inflation shock by increasing their policy rates or signaling they will do so if needed. The global AI boom is driving stronger growth in economies that are key parts of the AI supply chain. It's also
driving higher global prices for some AI related technologies that are supply constrained. So far, global demand pressures have largely been concentrated in AI related supply chains.
And domestically, while labor market conditions have eased gradually as expected, some capacity pressures remain. There is a risk that this could exacerbate the degree of pass through of
rising input costs. In terms of domestic activity, recent data have been broadly consistent with our expectation that demand growth would ease in the first half of 2026 following
a period of above trend growth late last year. Because monetary policy works with a lag, the full effects of recent rate increases are yet to be felt. The impact of the Middle East conflict
on economic activity has been relatively modest so far despite the decline in confidence with household spending growth moderating gradually. Business investment growth has picked up strongly
driven mostly by spending on data centers and renewable energy projects. Though investment in other areas is also increased. A period of subdued growth of aggregate demand is needed to reduce capacity
pressures and brings inflation down sustainably. Continued weak productivity growth means the economy cannot grow strongly without putting pressure on inflation. This is a
fundamental challenge for the Australian economy over the next few years. Conditions in the housing market have softened and a larger than expected easing could be a downside risk to
economic activity. The softer conditions partly reflect the usual transmission of monetary policy as well as tax policy changes and the broader economic environment. Housing prices have fallen in most
capital cities and new housing loans have declined. But these falls follow a period of strong growth. Housing prices are still around 50% higher than they were in early 2020.
Fundamentally, there is a structural underupp which has underpinned prices over recent years. Despite recent falls in housing prices, the share of borrowers in negative equity remains very limited and
only a small share are facing severe difficulty with their loan repayments. This isn't to downplay that for those affected, these circumstances are deeply challenging,
but it does indicate that financial stability risks are contained, including because borrowers in aggregate have built up considerable savings buffers over recent years.
I want to emphasize that while we expect housing prices to be affected when interest rates rise, monetary policy does not target housing prices. Rather, what matters for monetary policy is how
changes in housing prices affect economic activity, the labor market, and ultimately inflation. Lower housing prices can weigh on consumption by reducing households net
wealth. Turnover also declines when prices are falling, reducing consumption of goods that people tend to buy when moving house, such as furniture and appliances. Lower housing prices can also affect
incentives for residential investment and activity in the construction sector. The reduction in demand via these channels helps to reduce inflation. The monetary policy board will meet in
just over a week's time. We'll discuss our assessment of the flow of data and how the risks are unfolding. A key question is whether the tightening in monetary policy to date will be
sufficient to bring inflation back to target in a reasonable time. Monetary policy is well placed to respond to developments and we are focused on our mandate to deliver price
stability and full employment. I recognize that higher interest rates are difficult for Australians with mortgages who are also facing cost of living pressures, but reducing inflation
is essential. High inflation hurts all Australians and it is especially tough on people with lower incomes and those in vulnerable financial positions. So another key responsibility for the
RBA is the regulation and oversight of the payment system. We've completed our review of searchcharging and merchant payment costs. Following extensive extensive consultation, the payment
system board concluded that a package of reforms to remove card searchcharging, reduce interchange fee caps, and improve transparency of payment costs would be in the public interest and promote
greater competition and efficiency in the payment system. With cards sirch charging set to be removed from the 1st of October, we are monitoring the payment industry's implementation and
we're working with industry stakeholders to support merchant awareness of the changes. Following amendments to the payment systems regulation act 1998 which expanded our regulatory remitt, we
started a broader review of payment system regulation with the publication of an issues paper in June. This review is considering how regulation should respond to rapid
innovation and change in the payments landscape, including opportunities to improve competition, efficiency, and safety. The issues paper invited stakeholder views and evidence on which
payments policy issues should be prioritized by the RBA. In the submissions, stakeholders frequently raised issues relating to mobile wallets, three-party card schemes,
account-to-account payments, and agentic commerce. We recently published the stakeholder submissions and we intend to release regulatory pri priorities by the end of
2026 and start further consultation on prioritized issues by mid 2027. Many of the issues raised in these two reviews were also considered by um this committee in its inquiry into schemes,
digital wallets, and innovation in the payments sector. We welcome the committee's report, a level playing field. The report made 16 recommendations, including six directed
wholly or partially to the RBA, which we will address through our ongoing work program and regulatory reviews. In May, we published the project acacia final report examining how new forms of
money and infrastructure could improve the functioning of Australia's financial markets. In recognizing that many of the barriers to financial innovation in Australia stem from coordination
challenges, project acacia involved extension extensive collaboration with industry engagement with ASICH, APPA and the Treasury. The report found that asset tokenization
combined with innovations in money and settlement infrastructure has the potential to enhance the efficiency, functionality, and resilience of Australia's financial system. Since
then, we've launched consultation on the role of our own settlement infrastructure, RITs, in a tokenized ecosystem and with the Treasury reaffirmed that there remains no clear
public interest case for a retail central bank digital currency in Australia. We're working alongside ASICH and other regulators to explore a potential for thematic sandbox focused on tokenization
which was both a project acacia recommendation and is aligned with to the recommendations of the enhanced regulatory sandbox review together with the government's financial innovation
strategy. This work is helping to ensure Australia is well placed to harness the benefits of financial innovation while managing the risks. I'd also like to update the committee on
recent developments in the cash distribution system. Cash remains a critical part of an inclusive and resilient payment system. Although cash now plays a smaller role in everyday
payments, it is still widely used and values valued by Australians. Around half of Australians use cash in a typical week. The RBA remains committed to supporting the Australian
government's objective that cash remains available for as long as Australians want or need to use it. The cash distribution system has faced significant challenges. Lower
transactional cash use over recent decades has challenged the economics of pro providing cash services particularly in rural and regional areas. Industry participants are working on new
arrangements to support a more sustainable and efficient system. These will require approval by the AC. As the issuer of Australian banknotes, the RBA also plays a key role in
wholesale cash distribution. We provide banknotes to the major banks which distribute these to the broader community. We're continuing to work with industries so that our distribution
arrangements, programs, and incentives support efficient distribution and availability of cash across the country. The RBA welcomed the passage of the cash distribution framework act 2026 which
provides crisis readiness and resolution powers to support the continuity of critical cash distribution services. The AC will oversees oversee pricing access arrangements and service level standards.
The RBA recently designated Linfox Armag, a proprietary limited under the new legislation, reflecting its significant role in Australia's cash distribution system and making it
subject to the framework's obligations and requirements. Designation does not mean that the RBA will exercise crisis readiness or resolution powers in relation to Linfox Armagard. It means
that we have the ability to act if we need to. We work the work to operationalize these new powers and responsibilities is being undertaken in close coordination with the AC.
Finally, uh our vision at the RBA is to be an open and dynamic central bank that is trust for the quality of our analysis, policy and service delivery. We believe that provides the right
foundation to promote the economic prosperity and welfare of the Australian people as parliament has tasked us to do. Over the past three years, we've undertaken a significant program of
transformation to achieve this vision and position the RBA to meet the challenges of the future. This has spanned many dimensions of our operations, including governance
arrangements, policy and analytical frameworks, operational resilience, risk management, culture, and leadership. Last year, the governance board reported that we had largely implemented the
recommendations of the RBA review. Since then, we have completed the remaining recommendations, publishing a framework for additional monetary policy tools and commencing regular meetings of an
external expert advisory group on monetary policy. Nonetheless, we recognize that the world is evolving rapidly and that we must continue to evolve with it. A mindset of
continuous improvement is shaping all our work from shoring up the resilience of critical infrastructure such as RITs to our risk management, governance, and ways of working. We're operating in a
high-risisk environment and we believe these changes are strengthening the RBA's ability to promote the economic prosperity and welfare of the Australian people now and into the future. So,
thank you for listening and my colleagues and I look forward to answering your questions. Thank you, Chair. Thanks so much, Governor. Um uh in my uh opening statement I uh
referenced the um US Federal Reserve uh decision to raise interest rates by 25 basis points yesterday and appears a important moment to obtain the observations of the RBA about what's
happening in the global economy particularly as it affects our trading partners and I wondered if you could um reflect on any implications of that decision and additionally what the
reescalation of conflict in the Middle East has meant for global interest rates. Sure. So, I might I might start with the second part first because I think that's
what's influencing a lot of what's going on overseas. Um when the conflict first started there was I think a sort of a if you like a baseline assumption certainly on our part and amongst many other
countries that it would be short-lived and that the rise in oil prices and associated fuel prices and other energy prices would be short-lived and they would ultimately come back down. Maybe
not to pre-conlict levels but they would certainly uh come back. we along with others did scenarios in which prices did stay elevated for much longer. Um and in those circumstances um what central
banks were focusing on I think was the implications for inflation being more persistent. I think it's fair to say that those maybe not the most extreme scenarios, but certainly scenarios where
we're seeing a much higher for longer oil prices, fuel prices, those sorts of things. That's sort of more in the world we're in now. And I think you're seeing a realization
of that in the response of overseas central banks. uh there was a there was um a tendency to wait and see but now that fuel prices have been much higher for longer and you are seeing that
reflected in inflation overseas um central banks are responding and you've seen that in the responses as you highlighted particularly in the US and Europe and uh some other countries being
on high alert. We started from a slightly different position than many other countries. We started from a position of excess demand and so we had already started raising interest rates
before the conflict started and then we and we raised in February. The conflict started we raised two more times and then we paused to see how that would pan out. I think we're now in a very similar
position to other countries in the sense that we've still got a bit of excess demand and now we've got this extra impetus from a prolonged Middle East conflict and that is putting pressure on
prices in Australia to the extent that uh businesses thought that maybe it would be short-lived and they could perhaps wait and see whether they would pass price cost increases through. Now
they're seeing a prolonged period. I think there's much more of a inclination to think that we need to pass through these cost increases because it's going to be much more persistent.
So they're the sorts of things that are shaping our views I think and shaping the views of uh overseas central banks. Um and do you think the market's pricing in rate hikes in other countries as well?
Uh yes and what we've seen is that um over certainly over the past um period since the the uh conflict started we have seen expectations of interest rates uh in all countries rise. Mhm.
Um initially at least in in the US it was a bit different. They'd priced in falls and then they just priced in no falls whereas other countries they started to price in rises. uh now I think uh with
the prolonged um Middle East conflict what we're seeing now is that even in the United States we're seeing now that there are uh predictions by markets for increases in interest rates we're seeing
the same thing in Australia so yeah could I add one thing and sorry tell me to shut up if you don't want me to but um just back I would never be that blunt I believe you um just um just back from
the US and and and in addition to these downside risks so the upside risk of inflation from the Middle East. What is also very striking is how strong the AI and tech boom is and has been.
Um, and that's not just true in the US, it's true in the Asia-Pacific region as well, who are of course our closest trading partners. And we our forecast for global growth have been repeatedly
surprised on the upside. And so while we've all been focused on these downside risks and remain so, in fact, one of the perhaps slightly less wellld stories about the global market economy at the
moment is that in addition to these negative supply shocks, we're obviously also seeing at least some countries quite a strong positive demand shock and and Kevin Walsh talked about that at
some length in his own uh description of of where US policy was uh was going. So it's it's it's a more complex picture than just the Middle East or just these down cyber risks. We are also seeing
some real strength as as you said in your opening remarks. But can you u just expand on that a bit more when you talk about the upside uh in terms of what's happening around AI?
How how is that playing out in a way that you you see stats that make you and there's a lot of talk about AI and obviously its impact on the supply side and productivity and I'm sure we'll come
back later to talk about that. But actually the dominant feature of the AI and technology cycle at the moment is a much more straightforward investment boom. It's building the data centers uh
in the US and here and obviously elsewhere as well. But just as important is creating the products that fill those data centers. And that of course is what you know Taiwan and Singapore and Korea
and others are all working as hard as they possibly can to produce the memory chips, the servers, all of the kit that goes into those things. And so what's quite interesting, I think, is as we all
debate what AI will mean for the future, the initial wave of the AI boom has been very much more a conventional investment boom. And the numbers are huge. Uh they're huge in the US, but they're not
only huge in the US, they're huge here. And and they're huge in Asia Pacific as well. Uh and I don't think anyone I mean, everyone knew it would be big, but I don't think anyone had put quite the
sorts of numbers on it that we're seeing at the moment. Okay. Thank you. Are there any other um key risks that the RBA is keeping tabs on in terms of global economy that we should be mindful of?
Um well uh to the to the AI boom I mean there there's certainly some issues around financial stability that um some are concerned about. Um if you look at some of the things globally people are
concerned about. Um they're concerned about the possibility that asset prices u have run up quite quickly. Um and we can talk about financial stability. I could call on Brad to talk about that a
bit. Um the second thing that um many overseas economies worried about although it's less of an issue here I think is uh private credit um and the runup in private credit. I think it's
less of an issue here. Again Brad can talk in a bit more detail about that. But certainly overseas that's that's one of the issues u that um that we're watching. Um and I think um finally just
the whole um issue of whether or not so to Andrew's points about I think initially when the Middle East conflict broke out everyone was worried about the impact on the global economy of of higher
um for many countries not all but for many countries um it's been swamped by the AI demand side so but there is still a risk that with a very prolonged um Middle East conflict and very high
fuel prices and not just high fuel prices. If it turns out that there is just a shortage of supply, that might well have uh big implications for uh the world economy um in terms of growth. So
you know that to to Andrew's point, there is this demand and this supply side, but there's still this risk sitting on the supply side, I think, which um needs to be taken into account.
Um just turning to obviously everyone's looking a lot at global bond markets um uh and trying to figure out what's going on and why it's behaving in a particular way that it is but are there what are
some of the factors from the RBA's perspective are driving the pick up in in yields and how important was the Fed decision yesterday in terms of global bond markets? So global uh bond yields,
longerterm bond yields have been rising and I think um we would we would say they're not it's not been disorderly. Um there's still liquidity in markets. Um I think we'd probably attribute it to a
number of factors. First is um inflation. I think there is um an expectation that inflation is higher and central banks are going to have to keep interest rates higher in order to address that.
Um there's also overseas there's um quite a lot of pressure on longerterm uh lending funding markets because there's fiscal issues in a number of countries. There's quite uh high debt
levels in a number of countries. There's also uh increasing issuance into the longer term end of the bond markets, the corporate bond markets by the hyperscalers. So they're competing for um funding.
Um and I was hoping that you could expand on that as well because that that that seems to be quite unique in terms of this point in time. Yeah, sure. So um I mean up until fairly
recently, I think it's probably fair to say that a lot of the investment by the hyperscalers has been funded by equity. Mhm. Increasingly recently it's been funded
by borrowing and they're issuing at a similar tenor I guess uh 10 around the 10 year sort of the longer end um and at the same time as a number of countries number of European countries the United
States um they're running large fiscal deficits they uh already have quite elevated debt levels they're having to roll over those debt those uh debt issuance So when you've got more
issuance into so it's the supply demand uh equation the more supply that you have the more uh um compensation if you like for holding those uh those debt instruments that investors require and
then so yields are rising prices of the bonds are are are falling so that's that's what's going on in in that part so I think it's probably important to note that if you look to the extent we
can at um the breakdown of of nominal bond yields into real yields and inflation compensation. Inflation compensation that is staying reasonably steady. So what that's telling you is that the
markets think that central banks will do what is necessary to keep inflation stable. But the nominal yield, it's a real yield and it's reflecting a couple of things. It's reflecting a rise in the
term premium. again uh people require investors require more compensation to hold those those bonds. Um but it's also possibly reflecting the fact that what we call the neutral real interest rate the
interest rate that is sort of um neither inflationary nor disinflationary is rising and it's rising because of the very strong investment side of the equation investment. So again, more more
investment with a fixed pot of savings means you need the interest rate rises in order to um equilibrate those things. So there's a number of things going on there. It doesn't seem to be inflation
compensation which is a good thing for for central banks. That doesn't mean we we can relax because it's it's not a sufficient it's a necessary condition but it's not a sufficient condition to
make sure that we keep inflation expectations anchored. And that's really important. Andrew might have a few extra things to say. It is worth saying I think that that as
the governor has already said this adjustment has been quite orderly. It's it's happened it's it's been a reasonably large adjustment over the last few months but it has happened in a
way that markets have continued to function. Governments have continued to be able to issue both in Australia and overseas. Uh and it's the I would say it's the market working to be absolutely
honest with you. Um and there is a view in the market that actually yields prior to this pickup were probably on the low side particularly in terms of the compensation for the risk that holders
of longerterm debt uh might be required to to hold. So I you know this I don't want to sound complacent that this is somehow you know everything's fine and not a problem but markets are sending a
signal to those who are borrowing that if they wish to keep borrowing they're going to have to pay up for it and that obviously will have incentive effects as well. Um, I was in the UK when the LDI
crisis happened and a very sharp increase in long rates caused disorderly market conditions. This has not so far been an example of that. The only other one other thing I would
add is that to um Andrew's point, we're not complacent. We are watching it closely. Um, and we obviously are very well positioned in in the Reserve Bank. We have a dealing team. We have offices
in London and New York. We're well connected with markets. So we are watching watching closely but so far it has been orderly. And just quickly before I hand over to
the deputy chair, how's our how yields terms of Australia's yield moved? Um and especially in comparison to other advanced economies if you're able to just have a quick reflection on that and
then I'll hand over to you deputy chair. Um our yields have moved up as other yields have moved up overseas and reflecting very similar um factors. um inflation, expected interest rates, um
the neutral interest rate. Um so I think I think it's um not unexpected that everything is sort of moving up together and we're part of a global capital market. Um so um nothing unexpected I
don't think in that respect. Thank you over. Thank you chair. Um the chair runs a tight ship, so apologies if I cut you off and squeeze in a couple of extra questions, but um he's very he's a very
good chair. But look, I want to start with in your opening statement the comment inflation is too high and then dig into some of the the things under that. And given I'm in
parliament, I want to focus firstly on public demand. I see in the um August 26 forecast I have here um for the year through to June 27 so the same as the budget year the RBA forecast public
demand going up 3.1% while the economy grows at 1.5%. So am I reading that correctly that public demand is growing twice as fast as the overall economy or forecast hand to Sarah for the details.
Uh yes, deputy chair, we've got that's public demand as it's defined in the national account. So that's uh government spending um and government investment for all levels of government.
Uh so that that's direct spending in the economy um on services uh infrastructure projects and what have you. It doesn't include uh transfers to households. So that will be social security payments
and things like that. They get counted elsewhere. But just for that clarity uh but yes, the the forecast numbers that you've quoted are correct. It's 3.1% for growth in public demand through the year
June 27 and 1.5% for GDP. Okay. So twice as fast. And you just annunciated which was helpful. Public demand it's driven by payments public payments but investments and all those things.
To be to be clear payments as transfers to households accounted in household income. So that doesn't appear in that public demand series. No, it's uh direct uh direct pay consumption of services
and goods. So if you're building a a bridge for example, you got to uh pay the workers and you got to uh buy all the resources and things that would count. Um for government services
that are provided, so direct payments for healthcare for example would appear in there. But transfers to households, so pensions, um other social security payments, they appear in household income.
Okay. So that public demands growing twice as fast, but then payments are coming in in household income and they're also in there as well. So that yeah they so they appear um we have
income further down uh the forecast page the other side of the income equation is obviously taxes what households paid to the government. So just understand public demands
growing twice as fast as the economy and then payments if I'm not misunderstood they're outside of the pandemic at about a 40-year high at 26% of GDP. I so I don't have that figure to hand.
Um I think that the 26% of 26.2% 2% in GDP. I think I'm not Yeah, I don't have that figures to hand and I'm not sure if that's the figure for uh government spending,
public demand as a share of GDP or if that's the that's federal payments. I think I guess I don't have I don't have that figure at hand but that number is also states. Yes,
it's not just federal. This is states as well which public demand is states fed public demand is states federal payments is federal. No, no. In this public demand in the national accounts
is federal, state and local include states. Yeah. Sure. Y account for about 50% of they do. Yes. The the states are really quite substantial, which is why I know
that's not your focus, but it is a focus for us because we have to look at the Sure. So public demands growing f twice as fast as the economy. Um I note just because I I'm focused on the
federal government as you guys just pointed out. I note in your monetary policy statement, it recognizes the role the government plays in fiscal manage the role fiscal management plays in
achieving your board's objectives. So how we spend our money plays a big role in whether you can or can't achieve your inflation objectives. Is that a fair assessment?
Um so the way I would describe it is that um what we focus on is demand and supply of the economy. Aggregate demand is made up of public and private and anything that adds to aggregate demand. Yep.
And keeps it above supply is contributing to that excess demand. It doesn't matter whether it's private or public. So, so mathematically, yes. If public demand is lower and you don't get an offsetting
increase in private demand then that lowers demand and that and that decreases the um demand supply. Y uh so yes the answer is that it has um it has a mathematical relationship. This
is the way it works. Um I've said before and I'll say it again. It is not my job to tell the government any governments how they choose to spend their money. They are elected representatives and
they they make those choices. Yep. And that's what I'm focused on. But just to understand how your forecasts work and the models, all other things being equal, if government's spending
is, you know, let's call it 26% of GDP, so you don't have it on there. Um, if that was to fall to 24% of GDP, we in our side of the house, which you have no responsibility of, came and got
government spending and slashed 2% of it, all other things being equal, what would that do to inflation in your models and forecasts? Um well it would depend because it's
well if you just do that and nothing else happens but something else but all other things being equal if we on our side of the house I appreciate you didn't have control of it but all
other things being equal I just want to understand how your models work. So if I if we were to cut public spending federally by 2% of GDP how do your models work? How would they compute that? So um
what would happen to inflation? Yeah. So uh so the way um all general equilibrium models work is that they have a series of assumptions that you put into them and one of them is for us
uh government spending. So it we take the budgets it's an exogenous assumption doesn't change they come in u and then the model itself um has a number of feedback effects and loops if you like
that will then uh churn through and that's what we economists call that indogenous responses but you know things respond in the economy on the ground and then out the other side obviously you
get GDP inflation what happens in the labor market and so on uh so in terms of if we put in a lower profile for government spending whatever that might be um that would flow through um and
reduce aggregate demand in the first instance, but what would come out the other side really does depend on how the economy responds to that. It it is not um I'm afraid it's not just a mechanical
my question is to inflation. If you change that assumption in your model 26% to 24% what would inflation all other things being equal don't leave all the inputs we did that what would your model
say happens to inflation? So it would depend on everything. It would depend on how everything else responded. So for example, it would depend on uh whether the monetary policy
board chose to adjust the cash rate in that example. All other things being equal, but but but that's not we don't think about it that way because it's never all other
things equal. Um that's never the world. The world is not um linear in that way. Unfortunately, there's always other things responding and changing and shifting.
So would would inflation go up if we cut government spending by 2% in your models or forecasts? It would depend on whatever else happened. Um, that wouldn't I'm just asking you how your model
works. Let's say you modeled it and went back there now what would occur. You don't you don't know what would happen. We haven't we haven't done that scenario. Let's put it that way. But it
does depend on how the models treat things like what would happen. So it might even depend on where the the spending was cut. So if the spending say for example was cut in some areas uh
which um the um private sector was being crowded out of for example um then the response might be the private sector responds by increasing activity in which case it might mean demand doesn't
respond at all. If it's cut in other areas which directly impact consumption then it might be that demand falls and inflation falls as well. Would demand go up in any scenario if we cut government
spending by 2%? We've not run that scenario. You cannot run an infinite number of scenarios. We No one can. We don't have the manpower to So you've never run a scenario if we
reduce government spending in your models. Never. It would depend on the type of scenario we're talking about. To the government's point, it would depend on the composition of demand. It depends on
where the economy is in the cycle. if we're in a position of excess demand, if we're in a position of there being slack in. But have you ever run a scenario where we reduce government spending?
Have you ever looked at that scenario ever? We've not run that. You've never looked at a scenario where we've reduced government spending recently. Why don't you call us running
that scenario recently? Because we take we because we take it as given. Ahead of the next hearing, it would be really helpful for us because I'm the assistant shadow finance minister. We
look at government spending and given our mandate is how do we both work together to manage your objectives and we control the government spending arm. This arm of the executive, it would be
helpful ahead of the next hearing if you could say if we did reduce government spending, what is that doing to inflation? If we could have that ahead of the next hearing just so it helps me
in the parliament when we're talking with cross-examining the treasurer and shadow treasurer what that would do. It really we would Would that be helpful though? Do you
appreciate that' be helpful for us? Well, it may or may not be helpful for you guys. U but it's not necessarily um a helpful exercise for us because we don't control that lever. It's not in our
I'm just going back to your statement of monetary policy where we we recognize the role government fiscal management, government spending, which is the biggest part of that, plays in achieving
the board's objectives. So, I'm just trying to understand if we if we're not modeling what we do on this side of the house with spending, how that achieves your objectives, h how we actually both play
that role to achieve your objectives. Well, again, I I would suggest that that's that's the Treasury's responsibility to look at those sorts of issues. Our responsibility is to take
what is given by the parliament and then use that to generate our forecast and what we think is relevant for monetary policy. It's not our responsibility, I don't believe, to um make assumptions
about what we think fiscal policy should do in order to help us and tell fiscal policy what to we're not asking you to do. I just want to model scenarios because we there's
obviously a number of versions of the future that could play out and again Treasury is well placed to do that. Got it. Look, I'd like to move to productivity. um do you model different productivity
scenarios? So we uh we put out um a paper just over 12 months ago, August 2025, S&P uh where we talked through um what had happened to productivity in Australia in over the
last couple of decades or so. And as part of that, we downgraded our medium-term productivity assumption. Just to be clear for us uh that means it's an assumption on where we think
productivity growth is uh trending over the next one to two years. We don't go beyond that because that our policy horizon is 1 to two years. Uh that paper um in that paper we had the productivity
coming down to 7% as our year as our assumption from 1%. Um as part of that work we obviously considered um a number as a question on that that's okay. Um, so when you model that productivity and
you revise it down, just to go back to inflation, what does that do to inflation? Suspect you're going to get a bit frustrated with me on this answer. Um, it really does depend on how um the
economy and how people in the economy respond to um that fundamental. So one of the observations that we made um in that paper was that um if you looked at household income and household spending
for example there were two observations that we we noted. One um real wages so wages taking out inflation real wages tend to grow in line in the long run over sort of decades with productivity.
Uh so real incomes are very closely tied to what happens to productivity. And the the second observation that that paper made was that household spending is very
closely tied to household income as you might imagine. So um what happens to spending as a result of how productivity evolves? Actually it depends on how people see and understand what's
happening in the economy and generally over time people understand and see what's happening to their incomes and they adjust their spending accordingly. So um what happens to productivity and
how it drives inflation really does depend on the time horizon that you're looking at. Um what we're saying at the moment is that because we think productivity growth right now in a trend
sense is weaker than it has been in the past. Uh that puts a if you like a speed limit on the pace the economy can grow without generating inflationary pressures. We think that speed limit at
the moment is round about 2% a year. Just to pick up what you just said uh it puts a speed limit on the economy. So all other things being equal that would make me think lower productivity.
Well, it depends. It depends on where the economy is right now. So, if the economy where is the economy right now to take to take a step back into an abstract, if
the economy is in balance, if aggregate demand and aggregate supply are are in line with one another, then what we're saying is that if you start from that position, we think right now the economy
can grow at around about 2% a year without generating inflationary pressure. Um, right now, as the governor said earlier, we think the economy is operating with excess demand. So we
think demand is sitting slightly above supply and that's manifesting as inflation as domestically driven inflation. So in this situation where we are where aggregate demand is above aggregate
supply lower productivity increases inflation. Is that correct from what you it doesn't necessarily increase inflation. And it just means that when we look at what's happening in the
economy right now, we think that if the economy is growing at um faster, you know, materially faster than 2% a year, we would expect that to be a situation where demand growth is outstripping
supply growth and in that situation inflationary pressures are going to build. If the economy um is growing at lower than 2% a year or uh materially lower then that's a situation where we
would expect demand to be growing more slowly than supply. It's our assessment and in that situation inflationary pressures domestic inflationary pressures would be easing and then if
you're in the middle you're in the middle. So it again it depends on where you start from and where you're going to. It's not a mechanical straightforward situation. We could be
in a very different situation today and telling you, well, actually demand is growing, we think, a bit quicker than supply, but we're not generating inflationary pressure because we started
from a position where demand was below supply. Now, that's not the position today, but I use that as an example to illustrate. Unfortunately, it's not um a mechanical one for one, I'm afraid.
I think to just to just to sort of try and distill this down to one line or two lines. Um, at the moment, we think demand is above supply. And we think that product low
productivity growth means the economy can't grow very fast. So therefore demand has to grow more slowly than what we think the supply side of the economy is in order to bring
those inflationary pressures back down. So in in some sense um if we're from this starting from this position if demand growth is still continues to grow much more quickly than supply then that
will be inflationary. Thank you. Thanks. Thank you. Thank you very much. Um to kind of flip uh the deputy chair's approach to kind of the cause and effect. Um, I was
wondering if you could tell me when dealing when making, uh, interest rate adjustments, uh, whose spending are you trying to reduce and what behavior are we looking to change when we increase
interest rates? Um, okay. Um, I might actually I think Andrew, you might like to talk about transmission of monetary policy. It's widely discussed and this may be where your question is going that the
burden is all on mortgage holders and clearly there is a significant burden on mortgage holders but monetary policy affects every part of the economy that's why it's effective and I would draw out
four separate channels and we published research on this the biggest single channel is actually the exchange rate uh that's true we're a small open economy uh the exchange rate's risen by six
seven 8% on a trade weighted basis this year. That's quite a lot. Uh and you might think, well, exchange rate only affects people who are going overseas and so great, you get a cheaper holiday
and it can't be very important. It's much more pervasive than that. Every company importing uh products, which is almost every company in Australia gets cheaper products if the exchange rate is
higher. Um that's quite a powerful effect and actually in econom economic models, it's the biggest single effect of exchange rate uh uh of interest rate effects and that is true in Australia as
well. Um the second is on asset prices. Uh and again people might say oh well great if you're a rich guy with loads of equities you know but that's not most of the economy but everyone has almost
everyone has a superanuation fund. Uh and almost every well many people own or or live in houses. Uh and those effects are very important. They're probably the second most important channel of
monetary policy transmission. The third has this ugly term into temporal substitution. Sorry about that. Uh but what that means is that obviously higher interest rates increase the incentive to
save and decrease the incentive to borrow. Uh that's not a cash flow effect. That's not the effect that we typically talk about. Oh gosh, I've suddenly got to find higher mortgage
effects. It's an incentive effect. It's the one that you normally learn about in your actually in your textbooks and you know when you're talking to companies for example about the incentive to
invest. It's the most important factor. It's real. It's possibly the third most important. And then the fourth is the cash flow effect that dominates public discussion uh which is around mortgage
uh um servicing. Uh that's an important effect and we're very sensitive to the implications that has for individuals particularly those uh who are facing challenges finally mortgage but it's by
no means in economic terms the most important part of the economy. So I think sometimes when people talk about a blunt effect or a very unequal effect, this certainly has distributional
effects when we introduce interest rates, it underscells how pervasive an increase in interest rates actually is across all elements of the econom economy. H I'm wondering with the
distributional effects we uh saw some spending data from NAB which indicated that we there's very robust spending across age brackets but particularly in the under 25 and over 65 um age
demographics that seem to be less sensitive to interest rate changes and I was just wondering is the distributional effect of interest rate changes is that itself changing and does that and will
that kind of u impact the effectiveness of of these levers long term? So um I guess um it does I mean yes it it does have different impacts but one point that's always worth making is that um
overseas different economies they have different sorts of uh demographics they have different sorts of mortgage arrangements they have different uh and monetary policy works in all of them. So
Andrew I think spelt out very clearly the four areas we think it works through and it might be that yes it might have different distributional impacts. So maybe that impacts the way it flows
through in terms of intertemporal and uh mortgage but there's still the exchange rate channel as well and the asset prices. So it might mean that um the way it flows through in terms of the different
channels changes and it does have distributional impacts but it's still effective. I might just add we have done we do pay a lot of attention to transmission. It's
obviously very important uh for us to understand. We haven't got any evidence of um the the degree of transmission the speed of transmission uh changing in recent times despite what you're talking
about. So there isn't any empirical evidence. U and I think that points as well to um what Andrew was saying about the the relatively small size of the cash flow channel because it's got it's
got a positive and a minus. It might be that you're getting changes within uh that but because it's net is small. Uh it's not having a it's not changing materially in terms of the size of
transmission through the economy. That's good. Um so we were talking earlier about AI data centers. Um you're pointing out um Mr. Hower that the it seems to be a very conventional
investment at the moment in a lot of inputs. Obviously in Australia we don't make a lot of those inputs the chips and things like that. So for us is this going to be in the short term more
inflationary because it's mostly construction work which is kind of low productivity um at the moment and already um has supply issues. So, are we likely to see this boom being more
inflationary in the short term and and the kind of long-term productivity benefits being more um I suppose of predictory than than right now? Do you want to take this Sarah?
Uh, sure. Yes. Uh, so um so I wouldn't necessarily describe it as being um more inflationary than other countries. It is certainly true because we import the machinery and the equipment that goes
into the sheds. That's um it appears as an investment, but it appears on import. So it's not adding to domestic demand. Uh so in the context of the how does it flow into the domestic economy, you're
right, it is largely through that construction channel. Um but I don't think that that makes it necessarily more inflationary. In fact, one thing we're observing um in economies in Asia,
for example, is that the cost of those chips and those products that they actually manufacture and produce, the cost of those things has risen very very rapidly because demand for them is so
strong. Now that's having two effects. one that's means we're having to pay more. Um in fact um Apple recently increased their prices and noted that was because they were passing through
the increase of those chip costs. If you've therefore if you've bought an Apple product in Australia recently you probably would have experienced that. uh but it too it also means that for the
economies that are uh the centers for the manufacturing Andrew mentioned South Korea, Taiwan, Singapore, they are experiencing this boom on the ground themselves and that is causing them to
have to adjust monetary policy and they can see it in their data. So um I don't think we're unique um in how we're experiencing it, but we do look a bit different to some of our Asia colleagues.
They're quite impressive these data center construction projects. I don't know if you've been to one. I went to one recently. I mean, it is really the modern world in action. To your point,
these places are going up at enormous speed. The kit that's going into them is genuinely high um high tech. Um the cost per square foot, as I understand it, is higher than a sort of top- end luxury
flat. Um and the places ran with tradies with, you know, quite nice looking trucks that they're working on it. So, I kind of um the these are definitely big and real contributions to growth. Uh and
it's part of Australia getting ready for the modern world as well. say is it is it inflationary? Any activity is potentially inflationary if it isn't met by by supply side response. Uh but it
I'm I'm not I'm not sure that you there's a normative question as to whether we should or shouldn't be doing it. I think the only other point I would add is that um this is a conversation
going on among central banks around the world and um this discussion about the potential productivity improvements which is uh good for the supply side of the economy and the immediate demand side
implications and for many countries the sequencing is quite important. Um they're experiencing a big demand side now. they see the potential productivity in the future but is putting pressure
on in the short term and that's what central banks are focusing on now not for every country some countries haven't got the demand side um happening but many countries do and
and so we just need again to be cautious that uh we can see the productivity improvements and the supply side of the economy potentially out there but the focus at the moment is
that the extent that the demand side is is rising and and outstripping supply, we have to be very conscious that we don't let the inflationary pressures become persistent and embedded.
That makes sense. Thank you. I could talk about that a lot longer, but I'm mindful of time. Um I was wondering uh in relation to operation claw, which related to some bank uh mortgages um
being based on some false information as I understand it. I I note that in March um the bank's uh financial um review was saying expressing confidence in the robustness of mortgage lending. Um
however, OSRA identified kind of suspicious inflated incomes and misrepresented um employment and business information in a lot of lending. Um given that a given outcomes
and and reports that there could be you know quite a few u major bank loans based on false information about incomes. Um, is the bank confident that lending standards do remain sound in the
banking industry? And will that be something you're looking at before the October report? Yeah. So, I'm I'm going to give a brief answer in yes and I'm going to pass to Brad.
Yeah. I think um the proof of the pudding really is in the eating and by that I mean we pay very close attention along with our colleagues at APA uh to both loaner uh very high frequencies and more
medium-term frequencies uh and we do have a range of metrics uh that we review that speak to lending standards and that comes from information from surveys but also more quantitative information.
There's not much evidence at all across a broad uh swath of indicators to suggest that bank lending standards have uh deteriorated much if at all in recent years. In fact, um, frankly, the I think
there's been an increasing discussion about whether bank lending has, uh, bank lending standards have tightened to such an extent that other parts of the economy have had to look for alternative
sources of financing and that's where we've seen for instance very strong growth in non-bank lending in recent years. Um our assessment is on the whole that the non-bank lending activity we've
observed is helping to for instance uh provide the financing that's important for green field construction. Um uh but we don't have a a strong sense that there's been a
systematic uh weakening of lending standards. There's been some activity around private credit where um uh where you could make a case that lending standards have ease but private credit
is a very small part of the overall uh ecosystem of business credit in this country. Um and so our assessment there would be that um any weakening in lending standards in that segment are
primarily going to be a problem for investors who invested in those funds. Um it doesn't speak to a a systemic issue. Okay. One other quick point would just be to say um yes well aware not not
across the details of the individual sort of cases but yes there is an increase in fraud. Ora is obviously onto it. Um but I don't think uh there's there's certainly no evidence that that is going
to in some sense put the banks in a precarious position. They are very strong. Okay. Thank you Mr. Corbal. Your 10 minutes. Thank you chair. Um, Governor, just a couple of questions around the
intersection of the the housing prices and your monetary policy. Um, you made the statement today again, which is that um, conditions in the housing market has softened. Um,
and I guess I'm just I from what I understand, you don't expect that you would set policy to target house prices. So that's understood, but that house prices would be a
consideration in monetary policy. Um, so given what's happening at the moment, um, that I guess will be top of mind when you have your next decision come out. Um, you had also previously said,
you know, it's not your area of expertise. You rely on treasury modeling, etc. Um, so I can only assume you were provided with the treasury modeling. has what's occurred in real
life sort of aligned broadly with the treasury modeling that you were provided um in that sense um on the specifics of the modeling I'd have to defer to Sarah I I just want to
uh make uh one thing clear up front clarify one thing up front though you're talking about treasury modeling on the tax changes are you about well yeah I guess yes that's right yeah
post we have we have in our models We we have um we basically have sort of some uh ideas about what housing prices how housing prices might respond to interest rate rises and
that factors into our forecasts for growth and inflation and those sorts of things but you're talking specifically about modeling. That's correct. Sorry I should have clarified. Yeah.
Okay. So I I will defer to Sarah on that. Uh so um so our understanding of the Treasury modeling that was um uh put into the budget uh was that they were looking at the long-term implications of
the tax changes and um I I don't have the numbers to hand but that that was what they were reporting. Um to to pick up on what the the governor just said, we're very much more
concerned in fact primarily concerned with what's happening in the housing market in what you might call the short term, the here and now over the next couple of years. uh it's impacted by a
number of different factors uh that the governor mentioned uh in her opening statement and so we consider everything together again because we're concerned with the aggregate what that means for
um you know dwelling construction activity for the wealth effects uh for you know uh churn in the housing market itself and that's what then really matters for us in the context of
monetary policy so I think they're they're two different uh things but that's my understanding of the treasury modeling and so just going back we had the budget in May in the in August you'd sort of
come out and identified the interest rates the tax changes and weaker sentiment as what the factors were feeding in. I guess has your thinking evolved around what those inputs are and and sort of
the waiting that could be given to any one of those factors. It's very that's very very challenging. We think all of those factors are in there somewhere. um we normally would expect as we said a
response to interest rate rises and and not just actual interest rate rises expectations of interest rate rises. So if you look at what was happening to the housing market it had already started to
ease um at the end of last year and that was partly I think reflecting the fact that there was expectations building that interest rate rises were in the uh in the future. So, so I think um we do
expect that and so now how much is due to tax changes and how much is due to interest rates and how much is just due to households being concerned and worried about the conflict in the Middle
East and what it might mean for other things uh is very hard to to dissect. So I wouldn't like to put weights on any of it. I think they're all impacting. So in terms of your interest rate thoughts,
the the Treasury modeling was much more of a long run kind of a forecast and it was pretty modest. Like it was actually a very low dip off the business as usual, you might say. But I
mean given that we've seen some pretty sharp sharp softening if I can put it that way. I mean is that more of a contemplation for you now than it was say in August?
I I wouldn't say more and I wouldn't say less. It's always part of our thinking about what's going on in the broader economy. Uh what we talked about about how the housing market impacts
consumption, how it impacts housing construction. One point I would make though is that um there is still a structural under supply of housing and and so although um housing prices uh
have fallen, they are still up substantially on that where they were um six years ago. Um and the falls are actually not that big in in the uh scheme of things and under uh with with
a structural under supply of housing ultimately supply and demand is going to reassert itself. So you know yes people seem to be at the moment standing back a bit from the
market. Buyers are thinking prices might fall further. sellers are a little reluctant to sell because they they're getting less than they thought they would. So, there's this sort of
uncertainty in the market. And is that is that playing out in the rental market? I mean, is that that sort of baked in under supply? What's actually underpinning the constant rises
in rentals regardless of what the values are doing? Well, there is again vacancy rates in rental are very, very low. And there's these shortrun impacts about um what
might happen with investor housing and what that might mean for renters, but does that ultimately mean in the longer run that people who were renters can now be first home buyers? So there's a whole
sort of um there's these shortrun impacts and then then there's once things settle down, where is it going to settle down? Is it going to settle down with a a different mix of investors,
first home buyers, owner occupiers? That's that's the question. Sorry, you want to add? Yeah, just on the rental market. Um, so it's that market generally is a lot less
volatile than the established housing market. Rents don't go up and down the same way house prices do. They don't have the same kind of cycles. Um, as the governor was saying, um,
rental uh, market outcomes really are driven by demand and supply today. And in as much as the um the fall in house prices that's currently taking place of that uh dissuades some construction
activity because you know a developer might find their projects not viable now when he it might otherwise have been that new supply into the rental market if that was where it was going. That's
sort of uh one to two years down the track. So the project not getting off the ground today has implications for the rental market into the future. the rental market today is is a product an
outcome if you like of what's has happened to supply in the last few years and what has happened to demand. Then just one last quick one just in relation to the the interest
rates generally we sort of we got to 4.35 we cut you know we've now gone back up to 4.35 so we're we're back to where we were at the the previous peak in this cycle I mean is it your estimation that
actually that next.25 25 or or whatever a rate rise could be would actually have a greater impact um that in terms of its you know it's it's over what people have previously
had to budget in their expenditure. Are we would we see that as having an even more magnified effect at that point? um well not necessarily because um the cash rate is only one thing that
determines what we'd call financial conditions and financial conditions is really what um we're trying to influence here. So there's a question about um we've got the same cash rate but our
financial conditions similar? Now, one thing that's a little bit different now is that other central banks are raising interest rates overseas. And to Andrew's point about the exchange rate being
quite an important uh way that monetary policy filters through the economy, um if when when we were at 4.35 last other central banks were lowering interest rates. So that was sort of meant
supporting the exchange rate. to the extent that others are raising this time then that means that financial conditions might actually if we if if we same cash rate might be a little bit
looser than they were at the same cash rate. So so it's it's complicated. Um we we just we have to what we have to do is we have to set the rate at we think is because we've got excess demand at the
moment. We have to set it at a rate that we think is tight financial conditions to bring demand or slow demand enough to bring it back into line with supply. And it may be that that the same rate is
enough to do that. It may be that it's not. And that's really where we're we're at the moment thinking about where those upside risks lie and whether or not we've got tight enough policy to deliver
inflation back to target. Thank you. Thank you very much. Over to you. Thank you. Um I just want to go back to the discussion around um bond yields and particularly austral the the
movements in the Australian bond yields and um obviously wholesale funding costs. How like you talked earlier about the impact of overseas developments overseas on that. Can you provide a
little bit more color and a little bit more detail on what's happening overseas and where it's really impacting um us here in Australia in particular in relation to um our bond yields?
So I'll make a few remarks and then I'm sure I'm going to pass to Andrew because he loves this subject. Um there's always one. No judgments. So what's going on overseas at the
moment is we have increas we we've got the Middle East conflict. Andrew's also highlighted the increase in demand arising from the AI boom. That's all leading to inflationary pressures. And
so what bond yields are reflecting are a number of factors. They're reflecting that inflation is higher and the expectation that central banks are going to have to
raise interest rates to address that. Now, um I mentioned earlier that um that the interest the the compensation for inflation in those longerterm bond yields has remained reasonably uh
steady. So, it's not suggesting that markets think that uh inflation is going to be higher. It's suggesting that markets think central banks will respond to that. Then there's the demand side that we
were talking about earlier that there's a there's a lot of issuance. It's coming from uh fiscal, it's coming from hyperscalers. Um and that's feeding into the supply of bonds and that means that
there's more to be absorbed. All right? So that means that people might need more compensation. There's uncertainty um investors if if things are very uncertain, which they are at the moment
geopolitically and and let's not forget the whole trade um frictions thing hasn't gone away either. Um uh I think um the Middle East has dominated things, but there's still random announcements
coming out about um tariffs and trade restrictions and so that's adding to uncertainty as well. So investors need some sort of compensation for the fact that they don't know where we're going
to be in 5 to 10 years time. So they need compensation for that as well. So that's all going on overseas. We're part of a global capital market. So we're competing for similar investors. Um and
so you would expect that as those factors and some of those factors are present here as well that that would be um leading to increases in compensation that investors are requiring for for
bond yields. But um that's my um let me give you uh two reasons why it's good for Australia and two why it might not be. So one reason why it might be good is if to the extent that it means
that overseas and particularly in the US is getting on top of inflation. Uh that should uh make the growth uh cycle globally longer. Uh it means there's less likelihood of a sharp upward
movement in inflation in in interest rates and economies overseas can continue to grow. That's a hypothesis. We don't know yet whether that will be the case, but it's better to be on top
of inflation than not. That should be good for Australia if it means a longer uh global uh growth cycle. It's good clearly to have higher interest rates if you're a saver as well. Um and we have
plenty of savers uh in Australia. Um two reasons why it may not be as good. It obviously if you're a borrower, high interest rates isn't quite such good news and and particularly at the long
end of the curve. The Australian economy is much less sensitive to long interest rates than say the US economy. We are we are obviously mortgages in particular are mostly based on very short-term
interest rates but corporate borrowing is somewhat you know less has has a somewhat shorter maturity as well. Nonetheless, higher interest rates at the margin uh will increase the cost for
borrowers. Uh if you're a long-term property developer, for example, talking to someone the other day, you know, some of the um net present value of your projects may be somewhat lower as a
result of higher interest rates. Um that effect as I say is probably rather smaller in Australia than it is in some other economies. And as we talked about if there were to be a disorderly
movement in long interest rates globally and a financial stability event occurred uh that would obviously be bad news not frankly not just for Australia but for
anyone uh that we don't see happening at the moment. Uh we are on alert for the possibility which actually brings me to my the second part of my question which actually was going to be where do you
see this all going? So what's your for what what's your forecasts for this and how and how you know how will it impact future monetary policy? Well um needless to say we don't have a crystal ball. Um
what um we don't forecast uh long-term interest rates. Uh we don't even publish forecasts for uh where we think short-term interest rates will go. We we what we try to do is set out our
thinking on the economy, our reaction function, and we we let the markets sort of interpret where they what they think that might mean for interest rates based on the sorts of data and and so on that
are coming out. Having said that, um we do we are conscious of it. We're not complacent. We are alert and um we do have a financial stability review coming out in 1 of October I think and we these
are the sorts of issues we we don't have forecasts for them but we raise what we call risks so we say here are some of the risks that might arise and so um as Andrew already said one risk is
potentially that there um that there is a disorderly um adjustment in asset markets including bond markets, uh more risky asset markets. Um if there's a disorderly
adjustment there, um do do banks start to pull back on their financing to the real economy? And that's sort of where we start to worry about financial stability risks.
um and and so they're not forecasts as such, but I think the area to your point about, you know, our thinking about um long-term interest rates and those sorts of things, we probably think about them
more in terms of risks and scenarios on the financial stability side than really in our sort of monetary policy deliberations. It's much shorter term. Um but having said that um you know if
if it were to eventuate that things were to um u have a disorderly uh outcome overseas and that impacted Australia then monetary policy we we have instruments that we can use to
address those sorts of things. We we have a balance sheet. We can uh we have um foreign reserves if we need them for the exchange rate. We have a balance sheet to address issues if there's
disorderly uh bond markets. Um Andrew has direct experience of this sort of thing at the Bank of England. Um so we do have toolkits. Um not just the interest rate.
Can I make one one final comment? Sorry, I know you're on time. Um I was at Jackson Hole conference a couple of weeks ago. That's obviously where the Fed goes every year. and Ken Rogoff uh
was speaking and and Ken Rogoff's long-term theory has been that this this decline in long-term interest rates that we saw particularly around the time of GFC and COVID global financial crisis in
COVID uh w was the anomaly not that somehow we were in a new dawn where real rates would be near zero and you know never be any innovation again and we're in so-called secular stagnation that in
actual fact that was the aberration and that on that argument we're now getting back to a level of long-term rates which is much more um which which is much more normal frankly in the long term than
where we had been. I think the interesting question is have borrowers adjusted to that new reality and there's there's public sector borrowers and there are private sector borrowers.
Interest rates were never going to be zero or near zero for a long while. We all thought maybe they'd normalized a year ago. I think my personal view, as a personal view, is that we're probably
rather closer now to a more sensible level of long-term global real interest rates than we were a year or two ago. That doesn't necessarily mean everything's going to be fine, but I do
think it's probably not sort of wow, how do we explain this anomaly now, but how did we explain the anomaly in the past? That's the more interesting question. I mean there's a a quite an active debate
um again among global sort of central banks about this neutral real interest rate and um has it risen and I think there is a general consensus that it has risen um which means that interest rates
in normal times are higher than they were as Andrew said prior to uh particularly prior to co during that period in in the uh up to 2019. And just one quick one, chair, and we
I've only got a minute, so um overseas developments like what are you watching carefully other than the war AI? Well, um we're watching what's going on. We're watching what's going on in the
Middle East. Uh we are still watching trade. Uh that hasn't it seems to have been sort of playing second fiddle, but it's still there. We're obviously watching developments in
in financial markets overseas. Um some of the things that we're watching from a financial stability perspective are you mentioned AI but this issue about uh is it a bubble which will have a
disorderly unwind. Um so that's that's another issue that's sort of on the on the financial stability side. Um uh what else are we watching? China. Oh China. Yes. Yes of course we should
say China. I think the only other thing I would add that is we haven't mentioned yet uh we are very conscious of El Nino and the impact that might have on agricultural uh products and prices
farmgate prices and then food obviously so uh there is a lot on the list as the governor has already said Elnino is an interesting one because um a number of countries particularly in
our region are very focused on El Nino. Yep. Okay, thanks for that. So, we're going to have a 15 minute break that only goes for 10 minutes and we'll be back uh because of my tyrannical side uh at
11:05. No, I was too permissive. You all had too many questions. and I'll hand over to Algra Spender. Uh thank you so much chair and apologies for not being there in person. I'm
afraid I had already things in the diary before um this was rearranged. Um thank you for your time today. Um I wanted to start off with inflationary expectations. Um because I know that
there's some concerns you that you have mentioned about embedding of inflationary expectations and you know we've had above target inflation for most of the last almost 5 years. Uh my
question is you know in your conversations particularly with business are you starting to see inflationary expectations already embedded in the economy higher inflationary expectations
are embedded in the economy? Sure. So I wouldn't say embedded but um I would say that we do have some concerns in talking to businesses in our business liaison program that there is
starting to be a bit of a bubble up of a view that we're not getting inflation back down under three. Um it's not um uh I wouldn't say that um businesses are explicitly saying to us that they're
expecting inflation to be 3 whatever but there is this sort of feeling among and and that is worrying. Um uh as I said earlier um long-term inflationary expectations overseas and in Australia
do seem from what we can tell particularly from market measures do seem reasonably anchored at around two and a half for us. Um but that's necessary. It's not sufficient and in
shortrun inflation expectations have risen and that's expected. They do rise because people tend to reflect on what's happening now. Um but the fact that um businesses are starting to sort of ask
the question um is inflation coming back down is a bit of a concern to us. Um I don't know if there's anything you would add from the business leaison. Yeah just a a couple of points. So u
just to really reiterate and add to what the governor was saying uh what we are hearing generally when we talk to businesses is that sense of um inflation over the next 12 months. So they they
tend to sort of think on that type of horizon. And what they are um saying to us is that they can see cost pressures coming down the pipe at them. So some cost pressures are already facing today,
but they're also um anticipating that the that those cost pressures are going to remain an even build over the next uh 6 to 12 months. And actually, that's something we've heard um in recent weeks
with um the lift in in fuel prices and the the sort of reemergence, if you like, of of concerns around what's happening in the Middle East. And they're talking to us about um how
they're going to pass those on um or not and and how they're thinking about that. Um but they're certainly talking about them as pressures and also about how they're thinking about that in the
context of um wage discussions with their workforce. So, it is definitely showing up. It's definitely uh becoming um a theme that we're hearing and it's all very consistent with the statistical
measures that we have for short-term inflation expectations. And I and I think you know I I think you know we're in this world of you know it seems to be a sort of a wave a continual
wave of exogenous shocks which are and you know doesn't feel like it's coming to a time where we're going to have fewer of them. So one of the questions is you know is this idea of sort of sort
of you know sort of gliding to a narrow path over a longer period of time on inflation is that realistic now do you think is that is do we do we think that sort of that narrow path and that more
gentle path is is really open to us as much as as we thought it was perhaps even a year ago. Well look it is a it is a good question. I think first thing I would say is that
we we do have a dual mandate. So we do have to care about what happens to the employment market and the board has consciously been trying to uh balance bringing inflation
back in a reasonable time with the employment outcomes. Um the um but the longer we're above the target then the more concerning it is that inflation expectations will start to adjust. And
as we highlighted after our most recent um decision to hold the interest rate, um we do think and our forecast, we do think that the risks are actually skewed to the upside in terms of inflation at
the moment. Part of that is the worries about inflation expectations. Part of it is the shocks coming down the supply shocks coming down uh stream at us not only from uh the Middle East but also as
we discussed from weather related events and layer on top of that the demand things that uh that Andrew spoke about the risks all seem to be sitting on that upside there. So um and the other point
I would make is that the these supply shocks, the Middle East shock in particular, it has worsened the tradeoff between inflation and unemployment. It it that's just a given. So for any level
of unemployment now, inflation is higher. So that's that's not something monetary policy can do much about. Um and um a typical textbook response people say is well it's a it's a
temporary shock. you look through it and uh and then it will come back. The trouble is with consistent supply shocks and persistently uh that's what we're seeing. Um it's
harder in those circumstances and I think most central banks would acknowledge this. It's much harder to look through when there are persistent shocks because of the risk that will
flow through to inflation expectations. I think we have to acknowledge that the tradeoff has um has got worse, that this particular middle age shock has made us poorer. Um and uh we can't uh we can't
respond to that by letting inflation get out of control. In fact, it's more important than ever that we bring inflation back to target. Maybe could I just underscore that
point? This is a very obvious point to make uh Miss Bender and I apologize for doing it but the board is totally committed to hitting the target that we've been given and uh you know the
fact that it is hard and the fact that for some of the reasons you've described the governor has described it's harder does not mean that we're sort of sitting there thinking well gosh maybe three is
good enough maybe three and a half or four is good enough. uh we are charged with hitting two to 3% and and in doing that to hit the midpoint and and that's what our policy settings are designed to
do and perhaps it doesn't serve occasionally for us to reinforce that point. We will do what it takes to get there. Yeah. Mhm. Okay. Thank you. Um I want to guess to I guess a a a question really on
government spending and I know that um there have been some questions already on this. I I know Chris Richardson has sort of made the argument that $7 billion worth of government spending is
about 0.25% um interest rate movement. How do you you know but how do you do you do you agree with that? Is that how do you think about that? We don't we don't we don't think about
it in those terms at all. Um uh we we are focused on on actual aggregate demand. We're not we're not focused on um what we've been through these questions before about if you just
had an exogenous sort of decrease in government spending, what would that mean for interest rates? That's not a scenario that we go through. Um and we certainly don't have any quantitative
metrics around what we would think would be impacts. Mhm. Okay. Thank you. Um I I want to then move on to um private credit because I think there are certainly um concerns from a financial stability
point of view of you know what is happening to the private credit market and this just not locally but also overseas. from that question of financial stability. um how are you
thinking how are you thinking about this um this how the the sort of the challenges in in this space and you know how much of a topic is this um at the council of financial regulators you know
how much concern is there so I'm going to make a few remarks and then I'm going to pass to Brad because his team's been doing quite a bit of work on on this sort of area um as I
said earlier private credit overseas has been much more of an issue uh that central banks have been focusing on in terms of financial stability risks. It's much bigger in the United
States uh and Europe than it is here where we still think it's relatively small. Um nevertheless, it's opaque. People don't understand it. Um and that always worries people. Um
I mean, can I can I jump in there because one question is actually the data how much how much of the data do you have the data you need to assess the private credit market for instance? So
does the bank. So the answer is no, we don't. Uh I'm going to pass to Brad to just talk very briefly about what we do know about private credit and yeah thanks governor.
Yeah, the the two major issues here are very uneven standards across the industry and ASICH has explicitly called that out that relates to governance uh risk management disclosure to investors
um all sorts of um questions around the reliability of valuations and so on. Uh those have principally been framed as first order issues for investor protection. Uh the other issue that the
governor touched on is data gaps though. So this is a challenge for regulators all over the world including in Australia. Um that there are just holes in the ability of regulators everywhere
to fully get their arms around and have a line of sight into everything that's going on in that space. And there's some active work here in Australia but also internationally to try and close some of
those visibility gaps. So everyone has a better sense of where the vulnerabilities may be um rising. The last point I'll just make one uh one area where we do have some visibility is
the upper bound on linkages between banks and private credit funds and on the analysis that we've done uh we don't see that in Australia as being um anywhere near as large an issue as it
could be in some other jurisdictions. Thanks Allegra. Sorry. Thank you. Uh over to Jerome Axar. Uh thank you chair and uh nice to see you all again, Governor and others.
Sorry for not being here early. Um I've just had a quick look at your um opening statement which was emailed through to us. Uh we touched on search charging and surprise surprise we got a
few question on payments. Um uh you mentioned um you're monitoring the payments industry's implementation and stakeholders. you're dealing with them. Could you expand on that a little
bit? Sort of what what steps are you taking in the leadup to the 1st of October and and Yeah. Well, um we're talking obviously to the schemes because that's very important
thing because the no search charge uh is actually based on their rules. So, we're monitoring that they're putting it in in place. We've been talking to the AC. We've been talking to
the banks. Um we've also had contact with um a lot of the merchant associations um to find out how they're how they're dealing with it and how they're sort of uh and and also how the banks are
getting these messages through to their um clients as acquirers and and the non-bank acquirers as well. So they're the sorts of people where we're talking to. Um Brad, anything you want to add?
Yeah, probably just also just engaging with the inquirer universe to make sure that they are fully aware of their obligations, their transparency obligations for instance to be posting
on their websites the pass through of the interchange reductions. We think that's really important. Um and of course they've also got uh responsibilities to publish data now on
merchant service fees. We just want to get more sunlight into this ecosystem. We think that's really the best disinfectant when it when it comes to, you know, excessive charges.
Are you satisfied with their responses to you today? Do you think they're doing enough? So far, we we are. Um I wouldn't I I this is a personal opinion, I suppose, but um I would be surprised if there
weren't some hiccups. Mhm. after the 1st of October. I I wouldn't be surprised if there are some merchants that are not aware that and maybe their choirs haven't got to them,
but um um I I would expect that um there might be instances where um consumers are struck with a search charge and uh we're making sure that uh it's clear that you know they should be who they
should be reporting these things to. Obviously um the AC is in charge of misleading pricing but these are scheme rules so uh people should be taking it up with the merchant and uh and the
scheme should be dealing with it. So so in the example where um you know the search charge isn't automatically added added by either the point of sale or the um terminal. Uh that's where you
think there might be a hiccup in some of that manual application. That should have all been addressed. The acquirers should have all addressed that that that they should
have um updated their terminals and software and so on to make sure that search charges uh were not being added. Uh but um I'm I'm not brave enough to say there might be the odd hiccup.
Mr. Jones, you mentioned the pass through of the saving. What measures are you taking to monitor that? Well, as I said there, uh the large acquirers are going to be required to
publish by the end of the year um uh the degree to which they have passed through um the up upstream savings. The other apart from the interchange reductions, the other piece uh that we heard very
strongly in our review but also actually came through strongly in the review um that some members of this committee uh uh helped drive was um merchant service fees are also an issue and the lack of
transparency. Basically, merchants have no idea what they've been charged and and so um we're also requiring acquirers to publish that information uh on their websites and merchants will
have a better ability on their statements to see exactly what they're what they're being charged. So, all of those measures are, as I said, designed to create more transparency and and
sunlight. And our sense is that will help empower merchants to shop around because they'll actually know what they're being charged for. You said by the end of the year so they
don't have to publish on the 1st of October. They have to publish by the end end of that. That's right. Okay. Um and I will it be published in a way that uh merchants can sort of easily look at
before and after or will they have to dig out their contracts and sort of see what it was before and what it is on the 31st of December? Well, there'll be two there's two things going on. There's the
aggregate merchant um uh service fees that will be published on websites, but then each individual merchant uh on their statements uh uh will have a much higher level of visibility into what
they're being charged. The uh that piece comes in early next year. I think it's April. Okay. And it's your expectation that that that reduction in interchange flows through? Yes. At its maximum? Yes.
What if it does it? Well, we'll be um asking questions about why it's not being passed through. Um and uh we are already seeing the banks pass through the reduction of
interchange to their customers. So, I would expect to see uh it being passed through. There is a there is a a a second question here which is um and this committee highlighted this point about scheme
fees. Um and uh you might get the reduction in interchange pass through but to the extent that schemes raise their fees to offset that that's that's another issue and we're
very conscious of scheme fees as well there needs to be much more transparency about scheme fees. Um and and so that's another part of what we're what we're working on. Are
you looking at looking at scheme fees in your um uh priorities next year? Uh well, that was scheme fees was part of what came out of the most recent review. The the new review we're talking about
is focusing on other things, but scheme fees might well come up there as well. Okay. And um you mentioned in your opening statement so you you'll have prioritized issues by
sort of mid 2027 on what you're looking at next year like digital wallets, scheme fees. Yes. Where I think the plan is to take something to the payment system board
sort of in the uh last meeting of the year, isn't it Brad? Yeah. By by the end of this year, we expect to have a first cut of the issues that are going to animate this work. By
the middle of next year, we would expect to have um a consultation out on our prioritize issue basically how we're inclined to respond and and that will run for a while and then 2028 will
be the final basically final. It's worth noting that um there are a lot of issues have come up. We can't address everything at once. Um, so the prioritization process is going to be quite important.
Okay. So, you'll be looking closely at scheme fees to make sure they don't eat up those interchange savings. That's that's happened. We will be we we're going to be keeping
our eye on scheme fees. Yeah. Great. How long do I have, Chair? Got another two and a half minutes. Great. Um, in February I asked some questions about uh Easy Pay and uh your ability to
lease cost route to the cheapest debit service uh being FPOS. Um you mentioned in your response uh that you got capability for merchant choice routing in December 2022.
uh then in December 2025 you completed a multi-transition of customers to the new platform and then you were starting to do a technical discovery workshop with your acquirer
in a few weeks uh with looking a time getting a timeline uh to route to the cheapest available on market which would then save the Commonwealth money. How's that going?
Um I'll have to take that on notice. I haven't been briefed by the banking department on where they're at with that. Right. Okay. I guess my my concern is um you know where the Commonwealth has been
funding debit since the 1st of January 2025 perhaps. Uh and you've had the capability uh to have um merchant choice routing since December 2022 with your new acquirer.
Does this acquirer provide FPOS routing for other clients? I don't know the answer to that either. I'm sorry. I these are banking details which I am not cross and I will ask our team.
Okay. Okay. I just going back to questions from February. you know, my EO allocated $35.5 million of costs to absorb debit fees, you know, um, you've got the capability
to save money here by acquir, you know, by routing through FPOS. It's been 4 years. I'm just understanding I want to understand why it's been a bit of a delay. I understand. I'll come I'll come back
to you. Um, it's uh, as I said, banking department. I'll speak to banking department. Sure. And I guess you know a question depending on what the answer is is if your acquirer is it doesn't
have this capability are they the right acquirer for the RBA because the Commonwealth will be paying more than they need to given that there's a cheaper routing option out
there according to your own analysis. Right. Yep. Um okay. Thanks J. Excellent. Well done. Uh over to you, Julian. Thank you, chair. Uh Governor, in your opening statement, you talked about
unemployment rates being low by historical standards, and I was just wondering whether you might be able to take us through um how current labor market indicators for both unemployment
and participation compare to history as well. Um so um number of other things I guess the underemployment rate which takes into account um people who are working
but perhaps might want more hours that's at reasonably historic historically low levels as well. Employment uh participation levels are very high um as well. Um, I think I would also say that
in terms of forward-looking indicators, which is what we're we often focus on in terms of thinking about, employment is a bit of a lagging indicator. All the current uh um sort of forward looking
indicators like uh vacancies, quits rates, um those sorts of things um they're all looking stableish. they're not looking like um employment uh is going to turn downturn uh quickly in the
near term. Um but um it's worth you know we've as the unemployment rate has risen it's worth pointing out that employment has continued to grow. It's just that the labor force supply, if you like, has
grown more quickly. Um, and so the unemployment rate is rising. But, um, as I say, at the same time, employment is still growing and it has still been growing and there's been, um, you know,
a lot of jobs created and filled um, even as the unemployment rate has been rising. Is there anything you want to add, Sarah? Oh, I can just give a some statistical
context to to some of the the governor's comments. So just for example with the unemployment rate as you said it's currently at 4.5%. It's uh it's lifted a little bit recently but in the uh sort
of um I suppose 15 well even 20 years umish around you know from GFC through to to co um it was generally speaking above at or above 5% through that period. So when we talk about it being
historically low that's what we mean that in that long period before COVID um it was generally speaking at or above 5%. and that employment growth that you you both refer to, um what's been the major
driver of that? Are we talking market or non-market sector? Well, it's it's a bit of both. Um and uh if you look I think at the previous um six months I think it's probably been
more market than non-market but earlier on it was more non-market than market but um I mean yeah so uh the labor market um in terms of its composition tends to reflect what's happening on the
demand side. So uh over the last sort of 12 months or so um market the market sector private economy um has been the main driver of growth and that's been reflected in the employment numbers. So
it's been the market sector and private sector parts of the uh economy that have grown faster in terms of jobs growth than the non-market. And in terms of that um jobs growth
unemployment um I think at the outset you said that uh you know we're not alone in terms of the the challenging global economy. Um, how does uh our job growth over the past four years compared
to compared to major advanced economies across the world? Um, I don't know if I can answer that specifically. What I would say is that in terms of unemployment rates, our
unemployment rate has remained much lower than uh countries we typically compare ourselves to. For example, Canada and New Zealand whose unemployment rates um following their
increase in interest rates uh back in 22 23 their unemployment rates went to five six um ours has remained much lower than theirs. Um and uh the United States um
I'd have to say they've had very strong growth in in uh in their labor market. Their unemployment rate is sitting at 4.1 I think something like that. Um but uh certainly uh our unemployment
rates I couldn't speak for growth in employment but certainly our unemployment rate has been much better than many other countries. And New Zealand and Canada what what
have we been seeing there? um much higher unemployment rates, but they put interest rates up much higher. And this goes, I think, to the point that we've talked about before, which um you know,
some people have disagreed with, which was the board's strategy was to try. We got to a we got to a point where the unemployment rate was 3.5%. Um the labor market was too tight at that point. Um
and that was uh inflationary. Um but nevertheless we did try in raising interest rates to raise them to the extent that we thought we could bring inflation down while preserving as many
of the gains as we could in the employment market. Um the approach taken by u New Zealand and Canada in particular but some other countries as well in including the UK
and the US was to put interest rates up much higher. Um and at least in some of those countries the response was the labor market softened much more than it did here. And earlier you talked about uh
participation levels being up. Um can you talk about recent trends in the participation rate and um what it means for aggregate supply in the economy more broadly?
Um okay do you want to take that one? Yeah happy to talk to that one. So uh generally speaking the participation rate has been trending higher for for quite some time actually. It's not just
over the last couple of years it's actually more like the last few decades. Um what's been underpinning that has been an increase in women's participation in the workforce. So more
women that are working um and also a lift in the participation rate of older people um in general. So people uh perhaps working a bit um uh for a bit longer, but also women as they've uh
they may have entered the workforce 20 30 years ago, more of them have stayed in the workforce and so now they're still working um at in older age brackets. Um in terms of what that does
for the economy, it it does add to um our supply. Labor is needed to produce just about everything that we consume or you know all goods or services. And so if you do get an increase in the
participation rate for any given population, you will get an increase in aggregate supply. And so that women's participation is essentially uh having a a good impact on
the economy at the moment. It's ex it's certainly expanding supply and and in the context of um you know women being able to choose to do that and to be able to participate. I mean I'm a I'm a woman
myself obviously and I'm a mother. I very much appreciate that I can balance home and work. Thank you. Um I was going to ask in terms of uh the housing market. Can you
tell us um when the housing market started to soften? Um it started to soften towards the soften in the sense of the growth in housing prices started to soften towards
the end of last year partly in anti so prices were still rising but they weren't rising as quickly um and um so that was when we started to see it and it was also um again I made this point
earlier um we think that was at least partly in response to people starting to see that perhaps interest rates were going to rise. So, it wasn't just when interest rates
started to rise, it started to get factored into people's expectations. There's there's another thing going on here too in that I think um uh there was a sense in which
affordability was just getting very very challenging. Um there was a limit to how much further uh housing prices could rise. established housing prices in particular um because um people's people
just couldn't afford to buy them anymore. Um so so I think that was when it started to soften. I mean there's been a lot of focus on actual price declines. Um you've seen that certainly uh heavily
in Melbourne and Sydney, but if you look at price growth in some of the other capital cities and in the regions, it's come off as well. But um there was a very big run up in prices in those in
those and it hasn't come off quite as much as in Melbourne and Sydney. And you've talked about a few of them here, but um you know obviously you believe that there are multiple factors
impacting on that softening in the housing market. Uh can you take us through any others? Um I think probably I've highlighted the ones that covered the three main ones.
the three main ones, interest rates, uh tax changes and general uncertainty uh about uh from buyers and sellers and and so I can't think of any other factors. It's also ju just for a bit of u
crosscountry context, the runup in Australian house prices relative to all of our global peers has been very material. In fact, if your starting point for that comparison is prior to co
the runup in Australian housing prices exceeds that of large advanced economies, also the smaller open economies. So, uh the governor referenced the statistics in her opening
remarks, but it's been a very material runup and so we've seen 5 to 6% declines in Sydney, Melbourne, 1 to 2% in in the other states. So it's, you know, in that context, um, uh, it's it's not being
overly material. So longunning and multiffactoral. Thank you. Thank you. Um, okay. So, Governor, I'm just going to get, um, a graph circulated to you because I I want to
talk about the incomes of everyday Australians. This is a longer term look at what's happened in the economy and what will happen into the future. And I'll just hand it to you here. Um this
chart um based on the work of economist Greg Jericho talks about from May March 2021 to March 2023 the average Australian's real wage dropped more than 5% in value and I know
you're aware of this because back in May you observed um in the immediate aftermath of co people got wage rises um higher than what they were getting but they weren't keeping pace with inflation
so there real cuts in income. And I think the RBA's estimated by the end of 2028, a wage that was worth about $90,000 in 2021 will still be worth just under $87,000. And it'll be till 2036,
2036 that they get back uh to 2021 equivalent. Now, if profits go up above inflation, people will cheer that on. Senior management running those firms will be remunerated. Well, probably
pocket a bonus out of that, too. But the minute that workers would be pushing to repair that drop to their incomes above inflation, that will be perceived no doubt by the RBA and others as
problematic. So is it the case that Australian workers will have to continue to wear that financial dent for the next decade while others will be able to enjoy better in the meantime.
So, um I'm assuming this is the wage price index. Yeah, you mentioned WPI. Does it say that? It does say a WPI. Yeah. So, um let me just make make a couple of general points and then um I'm
going to pass to Sarah to talk about sort of how you think about real how we think about real wages. First point is clearly people are feeling the pinch and they're feeling
the pinch because inflation has been high now since 2022. Um and that eats into into their uh spending ability and and one thing that I like to point out to to people is that
um that is a bygone now. That is a new level of prices and the level of prices is not coming down. what we can do is ease the rate at which prices are increasing but we're not lowering
prices. So this is a a step change in the price level. Second point I would make is the extent to which the um the price level that the inflation has been um as a result of this recent um oil
shock that is a shock to real incomes. It makes us poorer. Yes, it does. So, um it's no surprise that people are feeling um that they're hurting, that they are um not able to buy as much as they could
uh with their with their incomes. Having said that, um I think it's worth thinking about this this measurement. I think this tells us a story, but this isn't telling us what people are
actually earning. And I want to pass to Sarah to talk a little bit about because other me measures of real wages show that real wages are in fact higher than they were. Not a lot but they are higher.
Um but do you want to talk? I've seen other figures that don't suggest that but anyway yeah I'll um so and it and apologies I it is quite technical statistical information so I I will try
and uh be as brief as I can but I think it is important to be absolutely correct on on these kind of questions because as the governor said this really matters to
individuals and and we don't trivialize that or take it lightly. Uh so this particular measure the WPI that that this chart uses as the measure for um nominal wages and then deflates them
with uh the CPI for inflation. the WPI the sort of core WPI measure that we track and that others track. Um it's a measure of uh wages that strips out a number of um components of wage growth
that people uh do do get and do come through and that's how you can get differences between this particular measure and the other core measure that we track is the national accounts
measure. So I'll just walk through what it strips out so we can get from there. If you could do it quickly because I've got some follow-up and I've only got 10 minutes. So um so it strips out um
importantly things like uh superanuation uh bonuses anything that's not part of your core wages. I understand super in particular you're not getting that today if you're a worker but it is um a part
of your your wages and you do get to it eventually as you age but it's not part of today. I understand that but that is counted in the sort of complete measure of wages because it is a a payment
that's made to uh to the worker as an individual. This measure um also only uh looks at wages growth on a what we call a like forlike basis. So if your job five years ago has not changed at all,
you haven't had a promotion, uh you have haven't moved to a different company, you haven't taken on a different type of role, if you're in exactly the same job as you were in the past, then then this
measure is the right one. But most people are not in that position. Most people do change their jobs. They might get promoted. They might get a bonus payment that's also stripped out of
here. I get that, but labor mobility is not as great in this country as it is. I'm not I'm not suggesting that's for I'm not stressing that's for everyone, but I'm just explaining why this measure
when you map it across to the national accounts measure, there is that gap once. And finally, this measure of um wages growth also strips out um about half of the wages gain that might come
from productivity growth. Now productivity growth I'll come back to that too has been relatively weak but nonetheless so all of that when you put all of that together and if you go from
this measure to the national accounts measure you actually as the governor said you do actually close the gap and the national accounts measure that we look at hasn't fallen in real terms it's
not growing quickly but it has fallen I just have to jump in so let's look at a number of things I I get that you absolutely and it's understood from the points that have been made here and
elsewhere um governor and to your colleagues the fight is on in terms of inflation and you've got a target between two to 3%. Um, and you know there is a point at which this will be a
easier fight to have in terms of repairing the financial position of low and middle income earners. My issue is this you also what the RBA suggested unemployment could go up that means
someone's losing their job. They can't push for higher wages because if they do above inflation that's problematic. um the productivity issue. If you look at the 10 years between 2010 and 2020, I
think productivity jumped by about um 16 just over 16%. Real wages only went up by 5%. 2010 to 20 uh 20, but they fell from March. Real private sector real wages fell by 5%. So that gets wiped out. So
my issue is this. I I don't think the RBA will ever be comfortable with real wages with you know wage increases above well above inflation to repair that loss of
earnings. And there are a lot of us here that represent people on $90,000 in their electorates. productivity won't you know the the the mantra that productivity if that goes up
that'll reflect better in wages doesn't seem to the numbers don't suggest that unemployment's got to go up to make the RBA comfortable and wages I I don't think there'll ever be a time that the
RBA will be comfortable if wages are going above inflation not just you but a lot of economic commentators and as they they say change my mind um we won't be comfortable while unit
labor costs are rising by more than our target is 2 and a half%. Yeah, I get that. At the moment, unit labor costs are rising by about 3 and a half%. They were rising by about five, but they're
consistently rising by about 3 and a half%. So, that is that's got inflationary pressure baked into it. And whileever that is the case, we're going to have to be concerned about bringing inflation
down. Um, as I've said before, we have one instrument. We have the interest rate. I acknowledge that it's tough for people. It is. And and I acknowledge that um their real
wages and what they're seeing in terms of their what their wages can buy is nowhere near what it was. But I, as I also said, um this recent shock, and there's probably more to come, these
supply shocks, they make us poorer. as a country and this is one reflection of that and um I just feel that um we have to I I acknowledge that it's tough but this is why we have to get inflation
back down I understand because and that's all we can do all we can do is keep inflation I totally appreciate that but say we get to the point where inflation hits that
mid-range point um And we need to find ways to repair that earning capacity of low and middle income earners like if it goes above inflation like the orthodoxy will be it's just not healthy.
And how is it that I mean we need profitable firms. We need investors that are happy with their returns. I get that. That's important to an economy. But how is it how do we get to ensure
that everyone shares in that in terms of the uplift and that they can go back to what they used to have instead of waiting to 2036 for that to happen. Wages can increase more quickly than
inflation. This was my point with unit labor costs. But productivity needs to be there. So you can have wages increasing by 3 1/2% and inflation at 2 1/2% if you've got productivity.
So I'm not saying that we can't have wages increasing by more than inflation. That's and and certainly the board's view is not that the minute wages are rising by more than inflation means we
have to tighten monetary policy. It's not as simple as that. This is why it comes back to productivity and the issues we talked about earlier. We can't grow much faster. We can't have faster growth in
wages unless productivity picks up. That is the bottom line. Okay. I I'm going to have to move to others. I mean, I'm not I'm not a believer in the direct automatic
movement of productivity flowing through to wages because the evidence just doesn't show that. But probably a debate for another time. Um I'm over well over time. Um so I'll hand over to the deputy
chair. Thank you. Uh the ABS shows that GDP per capita is flat over the past four years. Is there a time you can recall ever in Australia's history where we've had GDP per capita flat for four years?
I mean I don't have the full a full statistical table in order to answer that question. I don't um I mean it it's certainly to carry on the conversation about productivity. Um
it's certainly the case that uh all of these sort of per capita metrics when you strip out inflation from them anchor back to productivity. So that applies we we do think to real wages growth as we
were just talking about. It also applies to um household income per capita. It applies to GDP per capita. the these relationships are all if you chart them on a very long basis so go decades and
decades right back to World War II even before that uh you can see that relationship on that very long run basis so in the context of the question that you're asking um on a long run basis um
it would be you'd expect to see that kind of outcome when productivity growth have we in your charting that back to World War II you said I don't have the chart to hand that's
why I can't post the date you're not sure if there's ever been a period this bad? I think we we we don't know the answer. We'd have to go back and look at the long history. But I think the point of
Sarah's um intervention was that given that productivity now is so weak relative to history. It would be surprising if there had been previous episodes of flat GDP per capita
like this in history given what we know about the history of property. So this could be the worst ever in history of GDP per capita possibly. Okay, just well we don't know we don't know I don't
know that I don't remember someone else will have that to try I have no doubt but I don't have that to handle okay so if output per person's flat I'm seeing output per hour is down 5%. Can you
explain to me how that works? We're not producing any more per person but per hour we're producing 5% less on what time period you're talking about? Uh March 2022 to today. So okay so um so
it's certainly the case of when you're looking particularly through the last couple of years with COVID and the impact of COVID and coming out of COVID which is obviously early 2022 you have
to be really careful with how you measure productivity. the economy went through a substantial shock, a really substantial shock. We shut parts of it down, we then reopened, different parts
reopened at different times. So March 22 in particular is very impacted by that. So I wouldn't ever use that as an anchor point for looking at um any sort of metric to try and get a long run sense
because it's wrapped up in that COVID period. Uh but more generally um how can you get differences in GDP per capita versus not more generally what I'd like to let's take December 22 it's probably
down about 3% so in that time output per person's flat we'll take December 22 it's down 3%. How are we 3% per hour? My question is how are we in a circumstance where output per person's flat
but output per hour work is down. What's happening in the economy? Sure. So so in a substantive sense um obviously we're uh based on the number of hours worked and output the amount of
output that we're getting per hour worked has has fallen. I have to take your statistics as as correct because I again don't have them to hand. Uh how can that happen? Well a number of
things can be playing out. you can get some uh and we know actually over this period we have had some what we think are probably temporary uh effects coming through on at the sector level that are
distorting some of the aggregate productivity measures. For example, the mining sector is going through a period at the moment where output per hour worked uh per person in that sector has
been declining um quite sharply. Now mining is still in an absolute sense a very very productive sector uh very productive sector but what's happened over the last few years is that they've
had to um extract from parts of their mines that are are harder to get at the or is harder to get at and so output per hour work has gone down that's we think that's going to be temporary um there
can be other structural shifts that are playing through as well over the longer term we would expect that output per hour worked and output per worker would uh How do we broadly track in line with
one another? And that comes back to our medium-term productivity. In answer to the question, would a way to interpret that be Australians are working more hours for the same output?
It I think that in a mechanical what's wrong with what I just said? In a in a mechanical sense, that's correct. But I do think that the context matters and that's why I use that mining
sector example because I don't think that um necessarily most Australians outside of the mining sector would think about what was happening in the mining sector and and relate it to their
day-to-day experience. Just one one question, Governor, back to something you said to the member for Wentworth and I think you said um we've worsened the trade-off between unemployment and inflation.
Does a narrow path still exist for us? Um well, I retired the narrow path um a while ago. Um but um this idea of retaining the gains, as many of the gains in employment as we can while
bringing inflation back down, I think we can still have that as a as a target. Now the question is how many of those employment gains can we retain? I want to just be clear the unemployment rate
going up does not mean people losing jobs necessarily and in fact the unemployment rate has been rising while jobs are continuing to be created. So I think um we still can have that goal but
the bottom line and and uh the deputy governor said it earlier the bottom line is that we need to get inflation back down because if we don't that is a worse outcome across the board. So if that
means that we need bit more slack in the economy than we thought we did, then that's going to be the case. And when when you say sorry, I know you're being a bit playful, but when you
say you retired the narrow path long ago, why? I just felt it was um it we'd sort of we'd got to I retired it um back in the end of 2025 when we were experiencing a second bout of inflation
and I felt it was unhelpful to talk about this sort of narrow path. Now I thought it was much more constructive to talk about how can we bring inflation back down while preserving gains in
employment. I thought it was actually a much easier way to explain what the board was trying to achieve. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. I know that's helpful. Um yeah, just just on that what I guess
what's underneath my question what under what's underneath my question is given we've had such persistent high inflation and we're having these large inflationary shocks that there's just
far less room that we will are much more likely to bake in um price and wage expectations that will be higher. from these external shocks, meaning we therefore have to
um adjust more aggressively, therefore hurting the economy. We're in this period where um output per person's flat. We have high core or trim mean inflation. We're now having these exogenous shocks.
And I just worry now movements we do will further hurt economic growth be it absolute economic growth or economic growth per person. That's what worries me as a policy maker. So I'm thinking
through that. Am I understanding that correctly? You're understanding that correctly. Uh it is a well-known fact that supply shocks um are very difficult for central banks
to deal with and every central bank around the world is dealing with this problem and are they more difficult to deal with and we have underlying high inflation with our trend mean
for the starting point I think does matter and for us the fact that we already had demand outstripping supply so we already had inflationary pressures in the system I think that does make it
bit more difficult for for us to deal with and that's why we in fact were the first central bank to start raising interest rates. Yeah. And one more maybe um slightly out
of the box question um a super guarantee. What does that do to consumption and demand having a what do you mean if we're uh guaranteeing super or extending how much we spend on super a
percentage of wages? What does that do to demand? if we're going from 9 to 12 or 12 to 15 or 15 to 18. Um well to it's a bit hard to know really but but if you thought for
example that um in the block of wages that if you increase super means you get less in terms of your income now then it might mean that there's a shift in consumption. So less consumption now
more later in life when you you get your super. But I'm not sure there's much more I can say about what do I think that's right. It's how it comes through into um how the total wage uh
packet if you like adjusts and what component of that is workers received directly today versus what component is obviously put into an account for tomorrow. Thank you. Thank you guys. Terrific Mr.
Greg. Uh thank you chair. Um, I'm going to go to a slightly nerdy subject of the Phillips curve. Um, your research says that the inflation benefit of higher unemployment kind of diminishes as
unemployment goes up. We've obviously had a slight increase in unemployment recently. Where are we sitting on that curve at the moment? Um, well, okay. Yeah. Uh, so I mean, look, it's an
empirical observation. Um, it's not it's not a a theoretical fundamental actually. It's an empirical observation which we think captures some of the uh fundamentals of the economy. Um if you
estimate it at the moment u to the sort of earlier discussion uh we are in a situation where we have inflation that is above um our target and we do think that uh inflation expectations and long
run are anchored. So we're above that expectations point. Um and the u the unemployment rate is low by historical standards. Um and so that puts you on the uh we think on the steeper part of
the Phillips curve. The steeper part of the Phillips curve is the uh where we would think the economy is operating with demand um at least above supply as the governor was talking about earlier.
And so it it's a an empirical observation that captures much of what we've been talking about today. But but to your to your question about you know um when we were talking earlier
about the trade-off worsening with the supply shock, what that means is that the the Philips curve shifted up and out. So for every inflation number now the unemployment rate is higher.
Thank you for that. Um I'm going to jump around topics because of limited time. So I apologize if it seems nonlinear. Um the um with um with the searchcharging changes and the like obviously that
we're looking to implement over the coming months. Is there a program reflecting our recommendation in our report that we monitor the impact of those changes at a small business level
um to see what that impact is and is there a research project or a program of review to ensure that this is working? Uh well the answer is yes we are reviewing but Brad did you want to
expand a bit? Yeah, it's going to be it will feature ultimately in the analysis of pass through that we do because we know that small businesses were the ones who are facing the higher fees. So the
reduction in the caps will feed more through to them. So it'll be wrapped up principally in that in that analysis of um of pass through um and it may well also um surface in the review that we're
um about to embark on with respect to reform to the PS if there's issues that have come through and there I think we got 75 submissions. If um if we hear um more issues being serviced that we
didn't address in the first round of reforms then you know we're very open to looking at that. Thank you. Um going back to the questioning of the chair around kind of productivity and wage
increases. Would it be a fair statement to say that productivity enables wage increases, but it doesn't make it a certainty that wage increases come from a variety of factors, you know,
industrial relations laws, all sorts of things, but that it means that we have an economy conducive to to real wage increases if if we can get productivity rights, making it a worthy endeavor. So, so,
so um let me sort of make the point that um productivity and real wages over quarter to quarter um well first of all quarter to quarter productivity is very volatile.
So you need to think longer term and I think you need to think longer term about the relationship between uh wages and and productivity. Um um I accept the chair doesn't think there is a is a
relationship there but I think we would think that thing what the stats are saying overwhelmingly across time and across countries countries with higher productivity growth have higher real
wages that is a very robust economic fact over period shorter periods of time you can have changes in profit margin which I suspect cherry is where you're going and that companies in less
competitive sectors may try to hold on to more of the gains from productivity particularly interesting question in the high-tech sectors where there may be very little com competition altogether
but over long run assuming competition it's very hard to break that link and that competition would link to productivity so if you would have you know when you have more competitive
sectors you have more likely to have productivity but if there's no competition yeah so um thank you for that um in terms of the kind of global risks that we're taking
into account are there any kind of assumptions that we've made so far in all of our our projections that we're not so confident about globally. Um I think the one I would probably flag
in the context of our August forecast um and to to be clear it's a technical assumption for us uh was the profile for oil prices. So we used the market futures curve to anchor that profile. We
don't do anything to it. We flagged in the August S&P and as the governor mentioned earlier, we were quite concerned that that profile implied or was consistent with a relatively quick
resolution of the conflict and we could see uh plenty of ways that that might not play out. Um it does appear now we're in one of those worlds and if you look at the futures curve today um it is
certainly the case that it's uh quite a bit higher than the curve that we anchored our August forecast to. We were aware of that at the time, but it is a technical assumption, a technical
approach that we're pretty transparent about. That's probably the one I would highlight where it's a realized difference already. But by far the biggest assumption in the
market as opposed to in our forecast is what the ultimate returns to AI will be. It is such an completely unknown variable. But the valuation not just of AI stocks, but most of the nexus of
risky assets relies on that valuation. What how much will AI people be able to charge for their product in the steady state? Will China compete it away? The difference between the highest valuation
level and the lowest is absolutely enormous. We're all subject to that uncertainty at the moment. Okay, cool. Thank you. Uh governor just I know this is only very um recent
because it happened yesterday but the new migration announcement from the government um they basically announced new migration measures but the migration measures are designed to deliver the
same net overseas migration forecast that were in the budget which was 245 this financial year and then 225. um you've already, as I understand it, you'd already incorporated those May
figures into the August forecast. So, if there's no underlying change in those overseas migration numbers, is there any any need for you to change your forecasts based on that announcement?
Uh not in the context of the population projections. No. And we will update our projections as we get new forecasts from Center for Population Studies and that's
our standard approach. So if they alter their projections, that's when we would incorporate and make a change to ours in terms of where the reality is different from the forecast. Is that
what you mean? Right. Yeah. Well, so they're they're doing forecasts too. So they'll um I believe they'll put new forecasts out as part of my EO the next budget and so on.
We will wait for that information and incorporate that information when we get it. Um and then just further in relation to just growth in the economy which has been heavily reliant on immigration
and the the sort of growth per person is very flat. What's what's your view about migration numbers and the growth that we've seen in the economy? Well, it's um as you've already
highlighted um what we're the reason we're seeing aggregate growth in the economy is because we've got increasing numbers of people in the economy. GDP per person um is flat. Mhm.
Um so um if your question is going to the impact on inflation, I think we we have um often said and we and we do believe that um it adds to supply. So it adds to the supply in the labor market.
So it adds to demand, yes, but it also adds to supply. So it's probably reasonably neutral for inflation overall. Having said that, where uh it does impact is areas where supply can't
respond and the housing market is the very obvious place there. So that's where you tend to see the impact. But in terms of aggregate, correct me if I'm wrong Sarah, in terms of aggregate
forecasts, what we see is yes, you have higher migration, it adds to demand, but it also adds to supply. So probably the net impact on inflation or the the demand gap is is reasonably negligible.
But you're pretty satisfied with your observation that the housing market particularly has been impacted by the immigration because it's got a chronic under supply.
It tends to materialize in localized rent rental market. So migrants when they come into the country usually rent rather than buy. So they're in the rental market and um they can be quite
concentrated in certain rental markets inner city uh Sydney and Melbourne for example because that's where students live. You tend you can see the impact there. uh and and we saw that
particularly um coming out of COVID when lots of students came back and those rental markets saw particularly large rental increases. So that's where it tends to show up quite specifically. But
as the governor said on a very broad basis uh and over time as uh the econ, you know, the housing supply adjusts, they add to demand and supply, we don't see any medium-term impact on inflation
from migration. Okay, thank you. That's all from me, chair. Well, terrific. Okay. Uh over to you, Don Jared. Thank you. Um I just want to go back to um economic growth and that we've got
the two sectors public and private contributions. Um it is true correct correct me if I'm wrong that the private sector um activity has contributed more to economic growth than the public
sector. Is that correct? In recent in recent times in recent times okay so what are some of the factors that you've seen that has been driving that private sector growth? Uh well
investment's number one. Yeah. But what's encouraging the investment then? Well the the AI boom um renewables energy renewable energy investment is also part of that. The AI boom is and
data centers in particular is the thing that people focus on but there is some in renewable energy and I think there is some in other sorts of areas that we're observing. There's yeah there's been a a
general pick up in business investment but as the governor said um there's been a a substantial increase in the amount of investment activity in data centers um over the last 12 months really uh and
there's also been a pickup in um renewable energy as well. Those are the two main categories but there's been a a general pickup in business investment across the board. Um other areas where
we we have seen a much less uh dramatic pickup but nonetheless bit of a pickup. uh there has been in dwelling investment activity. So we actually saw um a lift in approvals um coming through in uh
starting in sort of 24 and into 25. That's now actually starting to realize in actual activity again that that sector has a bit of a pipeline. It takes time. Um and we did see um through the
back half of 2025 a bit of a pick up in household spending. Uh that has eased quarterto quarter this year. Uh but you can still see a bit of that in the annual figures and even the growth rates
the pace of growth this year although it is a bit softer than um the m the second half of last year it's still a bit stronger than we were seeing for household spending in 24 and going into 2025.
And just on that household spending are you seeing um different is there a a difference in households in terms of where that spending is coming from? So is it older Australians with superenuation like
what the Look, um I mean we get a little bit of we get some information on this from uh card data and and various banks provide information which breaks it down by uh
sectors um in particular um age groups um and um I think we have uh typically observed that older age groups are spending a bit more quickly and some of the the middle-aged groups. Um is there
anything else really much more middle age groups being what what uh people probably who who have mortgages so people with families and mortgages. So maybe the younger and the older
are spending uh growth growth in spending is a bit more than than people. So there's there's that that's been a feature of um the data I think for a few years actually.
Yeah. I mean I would add that uh just to add to what the governor said and and that's absolutely right in terms of that distribution but you can also see the broad trends across all groups. So all
groups saw a bit of a pick up through the back half of last year. All groups have seen a bit of a softening this year. So there's um most of what drives consumer spending is aggregate factors.
So what's happening to inflation for example, what's happening to household incomes and um even though different groups have different trends within there are always broad trends that
really are the anchor point and the driver. Yeah. Okay. I just want to go back to private credit markets actually because I know you've said it's been less of an issue in Australia but there are some
concerns in terms of that market overseas. You talked earlier about it's a bit opaque and we know that asex got some concerns about it. um what are you seeing overseas that is different to
here given understanding that it is an opaque area for you but to be able to say that there must be things happening overseas that you're seeing more of than we're seeing here.
Um I'll have a couple of reactions. Brad might have a few reactions as well. I think a few things. The first is that it's much bigger overseas. It's a much bigger uh share of if you think of the
universe of sort of bank financial institution lending and then non-bank financial institution lending. Um non-bank financial institution lending overseas is much bigger relative
to the financial sector than it is in Australia. Um and private credit is a much bigger chunk uh of um lending overseas than it is here. So that's the first thing. The
second thing, this is where the data opakeness comes in. Um, there is a feeling that there are increasing links to the financial sector overseas. Brad already spoke to the point that in
Australia we don't see that so much, but I think there's increasingly cons uh increasing concern overseas that um the links to the formal financial sector, the banks are actually um increasing and
is much stronger. So if the private credit market um uh there's a big implosion in the private credit market, it will wash back onto the banks and the financial system and if it does that
then that might impact the way banks are thinking about their own credit provision and so on. So they'd be my first couple of reactions. I don't know if you Yeah. And if Dr. James you can keep it
tight. So we've gone over and we've got three other members and we finish at 12:30. So welcome to my sharing. We'll leave it there. Is that unless there's anything quick you wanted to add before
I go to very quickly greater marketing to retail in the US in particular which is a different feature to Australia. Um more concern overseas about insurers interacting with private credit uh in a
way that we don't hear a lot about here in Australia. And the final piece is the actual loan portfolios uh are particularly in US private credit funds are more exposed to the disruption
that's going on in AI. A lot of our private credit has gone into commercial real estate for instance. So they're the main differences. Thank you. Allegra Spender. Thank you. Um I wanted to return to
productivity. Um and you know I think it's critical to growth in wages and also to fighting inflation. So I'm interested in your perspective on whether you have any you know it's it's
been a very hard area though to predict what's going to happen to productivity in in recent years. Um how when you're looking at your leading indicators are there any on that you look at in terms
of productivity and what are you seeing? Oh goodness. Um there are as you say it's very hard to predict and forecast. there aren't really any lead indicators that we would look at um that will give
us particularly good sights on what might happen to productivity. Um there are historical relationships though that we can um that we can see. For example, we just talked about business
investment. We do know that capital deepening um is a source of labor productivity. If you upgrade your capital stock um you you would expect to make your workers more productive and so
that would then uh lift your labor productivity. Uh we're also of course tracking uh we haven't talked about it too much but the impact of AI and thinking about that more on the longer
term and what that might do to productivity. We aren't seeing any signs of that in the um the actual data yet but it is very early. I wouldn't expect to be seeing signs of it in the data yet
but that will be a watch point for us um going forward from here for sure. But yeah no there are not good lead indicators for productivity unfortunately. Um yeah you have to rely
on history I'm afraid. Okay thank you. Um I then wanted to talk about um the RBA and how people understand the work that you do and including interest rates because there's
obviously a great deal of concern in the community about higher interest rates and inflation. Um but I understand in a recent survey that you did over half of Australians don't understand how
interest rates impact inflation. Um and um and don't really understand that sort of mechanisms. So I'm interested in, you know, is this a particularly Australian phenomenon and how are you thinking
about this because it sort of goes to some of the trust and unrest and unhappiness I think of of the community. Um a couple of couple of quick points. Um first of all um we are trying to
address this through public education. Um um deputy governor earlier went through how we think about the transmission of monetary policy. monetary policy works in all countries
regardless of their um their structures and their um particularly their you know the issue of the cash flow channel and so on. So we know it works um um in terms of um trying to educate people. We
are we trying to get out there. We're trying to explain things simply to people. Um but I do understand that for people with mortgages what they're focused on is that variable interest
rate. Um and it's very hard for them to understand why it is that we have to increase interest rates to address inflation. It's our only instrument though and it does work through other
channels. Um and you know Australia we're not unique but we're relatively unusual in um having a variable rate sort of mortgage book effectively. Um and that does mean that in Australia
interest rates capture much more uh of the public imagination than they do in many other countries. The the finding that you you site um in our survey is actually quite common
across countries and and I would say what people see is they see periods of high inflation are typically associated with periods of high interest rates. So they think ah one must be causing the
other. In fact the causality is the other way round. If inflation gets high for any reason, central banks usually have to have raised interest rates to bring it down. And I don't I actually
think most of these surveys are not saying people are dumb at all. They're actually spotting something really important. They're just making slightly the wrong inference about it. But
certainly in the UK, for example, when we did surveys of this, we found much the same type of belief. I guess the last point on that though, if people don't understand how these
mechanisms work, does it actually make it harder to stabilize in inflation? um because of these misconceptions um of of what these interest rate rises are trying to tell you.
Well, again um around the world we see that monetary policy does work. Interest rate rises does do work um in terms of lowering inflation. Having said that, I think it is important that people
understand how this works and I think ultimately that can only be helpful but it doesn't mean that it doesn't work. The one country where the one country where this insight was put into practice
in policy was Turkey where the prime minister decided that higher interest rates meant uh meant higher inflation. Uh they've got inflation about 37% at the moment. So to the governor's point
will persevere. Thank you. Thank you chair. Thank you very much Mr. Lal. Oh okay. Jeez. Favorite pet pet student. Here we getting the medal. Okay. Uh, Miss Campbell.
Oh, thank you, chair. Uh, I was going to change gears a little bit and talk about projectacia. Um, so you obviously touched on it at the beginning. Um, in your opening statement, uh, final report
came down in May. Um, by all accounts, you know, the tokenization of wholesale assets looks like it has, um, some good impacts. What are the next stages going forward in very practical terms?
Sure. I'm going to pass directly to U. Brad for that. Sure. Yeah. that let me just take a what are we trying to achieve here it what we have observed is that the wholesale
financial system in Australia has just generally been less dynamic than parts of our in particular retail payment system which uh by and large we've seen basically be a hot bed of of competition
and and and dynamism and we just haven't quite seen the same dynamics in the wholesale markets. tokenization may well have a role, an important role to play um in the future of our financial
system. It's not the only thing and there's plenty of other things I think that as a country uh we can consider. So that's the context for the project and ensuring that Australia stays pretty
close to the global frontier from an international competitiveness perspective because we still rely on foreign capital in this country. we have to provide international investors with
a seamless end to end experience to come and bring money and put capital to work in Australia. So that's basically what's sitting behind all of this work. Um most
concretely the the next really big um I think initiative cross agency that will involve uh we hope all aspects of industry both large incumbents but also the smaller disruptors will be
establishing a a thematic sandbox. The governor touched on that uh that will involve as said not just ourselves potentially but other agencies. What we're trying to do there is create a
safe space for um uh innovation to move beyond just sort of ideas and very small prototypes and provide a longer runway for ideas to be commercialized and scaled. And uh that I think that um case
was quite helpfully made as part of the ERS review uh which was presented which the government uh recently tabled and the assistant treasurer spoke to uh at the intersect conference a couple of
weeks ago. So there's a I think there's a really um a broader push that will involve um really all all public agencies and um and big chunks of industry. Sorry. Is this the fintech sandbox?
Yeah. What we're what we're contemplating is a digital financial market infrastructure sandbox where you could have for instance tokenize public and private money and tokenize assets uh
basically uh exchanging at much faster rates and being able to do things that are not currently possible with our uh with our settlement and payment rails. So that that's the big focus. There's
other initiatives um that are starting to form up. Our banks have expressed very strong interest in accelerating their work on the the tokenization of bank deposits. We put out an expression
of interest. We got 40 uh responses. So there's very strong engagement now right across the banking ecosystem. Uh we also put out an expression of interest uh for
an advisory group uh that will work with regulators to bring to bear uh to identify the major issues uh that need to be identified and work through. We hadund more than 120 submissions uh for
that expression of interest. So I think what AACA has managed to do is create a bit of a step change in um in engagement on this issue and a lot of it's basically trying to make sure that
Australia remains internationally competitive. What do you think that the impact of the tokenization of banking deposits will have on consumers? Um, look, we are um there are today's
monetary system consists of a couple of tiers. There's the central bank layer which basically sits underneath everything. That's that's the it's the trust in money that we provide and the
infrastructure and the sort of level playing field. On top of that, you have banks innovating and other payment service providers innovating, providing consumerf facing products and services
in a more innovative way than frankly central banks can can do. And so from a philosophical perspective, uh there's good reasons to think that uh that tokenized bank deposits would be part of
this broader ecosystem where the speed of money, the way that money can be used, programmed, etc. the way that it can be used to accelerate settlement times. All of those things uh would be
in the frame and that's why banks are are looking into this space. I think frankly they're also looking at the potential threat that stable coins pose a and are looking to uh make sure that
they're not just reacting to to the emergence of stable coins. Uh because at the end of the day, the two main private forms of tokenized money are going to be stable coins and and bank deposits. that
if there's no form of tokenized bank deposits, the risk for banks is that all the all the action happens in the stable coin space. Um post the project uh you know
obviously as you say the industry has to innovate. Um what other levers um are out there um for the industry to innovate beyond the sandbox? Well, actually this is where the
opportunities um that the uh that the recent review into financial innovation, the whole architecture I think uh come to bear. As I said, it's not just about tokenization. I think the architecture
that was set out in the in the review of the enhanced regulatory sandbox is looking for multiple ways where you can have potentially complimentary financial sandboxes. one possible uh idea there
could be for instance an AI the use of AI and financial services is one that I've heard uh some people speak about uh so there could be opportunities for sandboxes to interact there could also
be opportunities for sandboxes here in Australia to interact with those abroad so I think the the opportunities are limitless the final question I was going to ask is
pace is obviously essential as you've outlined um what is the RBA doing post report to make sure that you know we've got our foot on the throat of this. Yeah. Well, as I mentioned, and in fact,
the governor mentioned, we've just put out a consultation uh to the public on how our settlement infrastructure can evolve over time to accommodate and facilitate uh
responsible innovation in the country, including tokenization. That what we hear back from industry will inform a much larger multi-year uh rejuvenation of our settlement infrastructure. So
that is a that's going to be a very big piece of work. I mentioned the sandbox uh for next year. Uh I also mentioned the advisory groups we're setting up and uh uh helping to coordinate for banks on
tokenized bank deposits and also on a much wider range of tokenization initiatives as well. We're also contemplating some crossber initiatives because none of us are satisfied uh with
where uh the speed or cost of crossber payments are at. So there's there's multiple things we've got in the pot. Thank you. Thanks. I I don't want to be Debbie Downer on it, but I've watched that
fintech sandbox for years. We've been pumping air into that puncture dire. I hope these I hope these changes work because it's been around for two different administrations and it's yet to yield.
Yep. We've got to do some things differently. Um just uh using my chair's prerogative of being able to jump in with it. Just a few minutes left. I don't want to verbal
you, Dr. Hunter, but I think in response to my colleague Matt Greg, who we'll condemn later for leaving early, um he uh put to you about data centers and that investment being inflationary and
you took a different view from memory. So I think that if I recall the question and I might not recall it correctly, I think he asked me if uh we thought that the data center investment here was more
inflationary than in other countries. Yeah, my response to that was that we haven't looked at that very specifically, but um I wouldn't expect that to be the case. I
think the way we're investing in data centers looks quite similar to other countries. We have to import the machinery and equipment as say for example the US does but everyone has to
build the shed. Um and so and that's domestic activity. You can't import that. Okay. And so that flows through. So for clarity that's what I meant. Okay. So I mean this is going to run into
billions. Like it is a notable like if you look at everything that's happening in the economy in terms of investment. It's massive. You've impressed upon us today about if
demand is over supply or greater than supply. That's an issue. Um part of that is capacity constraints. We're 90,000 workers short in construction. We've talked about dwellings and the
need to build more dwellings. We've got all the infrastructure that's required to support it in a context too where we're thinking about immigration changes as well.
And so this is the thing that doesn't gel in my mind when you make that statement. If I can just finish if I can just yeah just give me a tick. I just can't in my mind all that does not gel
with that type of statement. So to be absolutely clear um what we are hearing in liaison and what we can see in the numbers is that this type of activity is adding to construction demand. It is
absorbing uh labor locally and that is putting um pressure into the construction system. So I I sorry I did not mean to suggest that it wasn't inflationary in an absolute sense to
absolute clarity. I meant that it relative to other countries. So we know that um this activity is definitely um adding to demand. We're hearing through liaison about workers that are getting
attracted to come and work on these projects and that means that they're not working on home building on other types of construction activity. Um it's particularly concentrated in Sydney and
Melbourne at the moment because that's where these data centers are currently getting built. Um and so that channel that you're talking about is definitely playing through. That's absolutely true
on the ground. We hear it in liaison. Um but I but I've talked to colleagues overseas and they're seeing the same thing. That was all I meant earlier on. It's it it is exerting inflationary
pressure particularly in an area that we know is already stretched. Oh yeah. Look, just between us can no one tell Matt Greek that I said we're going to condemn him. Um anyhow,
we won't tell him, but I'll just send in the hands up. Oh, terrific. Okay, that was very helpful. Mr. Lau, I can't chip you because you seated your time. Um can I
just say on behalf of the uh committee, thank you uh yet again uh for your attendance here um I uh the committee secretariat will be in contact with you in relation to any matters arising out
of today's hearing and you'll be um sent a copy of the transcript of your evidence and we'll have an opportunity to request uh corrections. Uh can I also thank my colleagues as well uh for uh
their attendance and participation today. Uh and with that and also the secretariat, thank you for all all your work. Um with that, I declare the public hearing closed. Thank you very much. Thank you.
Hallelujah.